    <font color="#ff0000"><b>
    <p align="justify">#2179</p>
    <p align="justify">THE NATURE AND USE OF THE TYPES</p>
    </b></font><p align="justify"><font color="#ff0000"><b><a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Col%202.17" data-reference="Col 2.17" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Colossians 2:17</a></b></font> </p>
    <p align="justify">"These are a shadow of the things to come, but the 
    substance belongs to Christ."</p>
    <p align="justify">MAN is naturally addicted to superstition; partly from a 
    consciousness of his needing mercy from God, and partly from a desire of 
    reconciling himself to God by some meritorious services of his own. The 
    Jewish economy had rather a tendency to foster this disposition, inasmuch as 
    it prescribed many rites and ceremonies as means of acceptance with God. But 
    from these the Gospel has set us free; and, in so doing, has introduced a 
    more free and liberal spirit. Even under the light of the Gospel, we are 
    prone to indulge the same servile desires, and to prefer a yoke of bondage 
    to the freedom of God's children. Such was the case with many even in the 
    apostolic age. </p>
    <p align="justify">Paul is cautioning the Colossians against two sorts of 
    teachers, who were endeavoring to mislead them; against the advocates for 
    heathen philosophy, verse 8, and against the Judaizing brethren, who 
    insisted on the observance of the Mosaic ritual, verse 16. In opposition to 
    the latter of these, he bids the Christians to assert their liberty from the 
    observances of the ceremonial law, that being, in fact, no more than a <i>
    shadow</i>, of which they now possessed the <i>substance</i>.</p>
    <p align="justify">We shall take occasion from his words to show,</p>
    <font color="#0000ff"><b>
    <p align="justify">I. The nature of the types—</p>
    </b></font>
    <p align="justify">The Scripture sets before us several kinds of types—</p>
    <p align="justify">Christians are in general but little acquainted with the 
    types: yet the scripture abounds with them, and mentions various kinds of 
    them. They may be reduced to three classes; natural, historical, and legal.
    </p>
    <p align="justify">The <u>natural</u> types are such as may be seen in the 
    works of nature (in this view, the creation of the universe is a type of the 
    new creation, which the regenerate soul experiences through the word and 
    Spirit of God.) </p>
    <p align="justify">The <u>historical</u> types are such as Moses, Joshua, 
    David, and others.</p>
    <p align="justify">The <u>legal</u> types are all the ceremonies of the 
    Jewish law.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">These are shadowy representations of Christ and his 
    benefits—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">All of them relate to Christ in some view or other; 
    either to his person and offices, or to his Church and the benefits he 
    confers upon it. They are the <i>shadow</i>, whereof he is the <i>substance</i>: 
    and as a shadow represents, though but faintly, the image of the substance, 
    so they portray, though in a very indistinct manner, the character and work 
    of Christ.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">In fact, they were instituted of God for this end—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">The paschal feast, with all its attendant observances, 
    was not merely commemorative of a deliverance that was past: it was to 
    shadow forth an infinitely greater deliverance that was to come; as Paul 
    says, "Christ our Passover is sacrificed for us: therefore let us keep the 
    feast, not with old leaven, but with the unleavened bread of sincerity and 
    truth, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Heb%208.5" data-reference="Heb 8.5" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hebrews 8:5</a>. <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Cor%205.7-8" data-reference="1 Cor 5.7-8" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Corinthians 5:7-8</a>." </p>
    <p align="justify">In like manner, we are told that all the ordinances 
    relative to the priestly office "served unto the example and shadow of 
    heavenly things, as Moses was admonished of God when he was about to make 
    the tabernacle: "For, see, says he, that you make all things according to 
    the pattern shown to you in the mount <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Heb%208.5" data-reference="Heb 8.5" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hebrews 8:5</a>." </p>
    <p align="justify">The Law was the shadow; the Gospel is the substance.</p>
    <p align="justify">The Law was the model; and the Gospel is the edifice 
    erected in perfect accordance with it.</p>
    <p align="justify">We are not at liberty to consider every common similitude 
    as a type, or to launch into the boundless ocean of conjecture: in some 
    instances indeed observations drawn from analogy may be almost as convincing 
    as the declarations of God himself. But it is safest to adhere to those 
    points which Scripture has determined for us: in them we are in no danger of 
    erring, and therefore can speak with precision and authority. Nor should we 
    ever forget, that, as those things alone are sacraments to us which God has 
    appointed to be so, so those things alone were types to the Jewish church, 
    which God instituted for that express purpose.</p>
    <p align="justify">The text, in connection with the context, leads us 
    further to declare,</p>
    <font color="#0000ff"><b>
    <p align="justify">II. Their use—</p>
    </b></font>
    <p align="justify">God would not have appointed them, if they had not been 
    beneficial to his Church. But with respect to the Jewish and the Christian 
    Church, we shall, as they subserved different purposes, notice their use to 
    each:</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">1. To the Jews—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">The types served to show them what sort of a person their 
    Messiah would be: he was to be:<br>
    a <i>Prophet</i>, like unto Moses, <br>
    a <i>Priest</i>, like Aaron, <br>
    a <i>King</i>, like David. </p>
    <p align="justify">He was to be a <i>suffering </i>Messiah, no less than a
    <i>reigning </i>Messiah. </p>
    <p align="justify">The types further kept up the expectation of him in the 
    world. The first promise had been nearly forgotten; and most probably the 
    repetition of it would have made but a transient impression: but the 
    multitude of observances, daily repeated, and continually directing the eyes 
    of the worshipers to him, could not fail of exciting a general and 
    increasing expectation of his advent. They moreover led the people to 
    exercise faith in him. Every intelligent worshiper must see that the blood 
    of bulls and of goats could not take away sin; and therefore (as we are sure 
    Abraham, David, and others did) the devout Jews must <i>look through the 
    ordinances to Christ, and rely on him who was to come, just as we rely on 
    him who is come.</i></p><i>
    </i><b>
    <p align="justify">2. To Christians—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">The types are of signal use to us, in that they testify 
    of Christ as the person promised from the foundation of the world, and 
    prefigured in the whole of the Mosaic ritual. When we compare the account of 
    Christ in the New Testament with the various ordinances of the Old 
    Testament, we see how impossible it was that such a coincidence of character 
    would ever happen, but by the express ordination and appointment of God. But 
    they are of further use to us also, in that they wonderfully illustrate the 
    fullness and excellency of Christ. </p>
    <p align="justify">As there are myriads of stars—yet all of them together 
    are no more than a candle in comparison with the sun; so all the typical 
    exhibitions of Christ are but a shadow in comparison with him: and "though 
    they are exceeding glorious in themselves—yet have they no glory by reason 
    of the glory that excels, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/2%20Cor%203.9-11" data-reference="2 Cor 3.9-11" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2 Corinthians 3:9-11</a>." To this effect the Apostle 
    says, "If the blood of bulls and of goats, and the ashes of a heifer 
    sanctifies to the purifying of the flesh—then how much more shall the blood 
    of Christ, who through the eternal Spirit offered himself without spot to 
    God, purge your conscience from dead works to serve the living God, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Heb%209.13-14" data-reference="Heb 9.13-14" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hebrews 
    9:13-14</a>." </p>
    <p align="justify">This is the <i>view </i>which we are to take of the 
    types, this the <i>improvement </i>we are to make of them. </p>
    <p align="justify">We could not have formed any adequate idea of Christ's 
    work and offices, if we had not been assisted by the typical institutions: 
    these serve to embody our notions, and to make them, like a picture, visible 
    to the eyes of men, and therefore intelligible to the lowest capacity: 
    whereas, if we could not thus invest them, as it were, with matter, we could 
    only offer to our bearers some abstract ideas, which, after all, would 
    convey but little meaning, and leave no abiding impression.</p>
    <b><font color="#0000ff">
    <p align="justify">INFERENCES—</p>
    </font>
    <p align="justify">1. How great are the privileges of the Christian Church!</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">The Jews were oppressed with a yoke of ceremonies, which 
    they were not able to bear—the import of which they could very faintly 
    discern—and the observance of which yielded no permanent satisfaction to 
    their consciences, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Heb%2010.1-2" data-reference="Heb 10.1-2" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hebrews 10:1-2</a>; but we are freed from that yoke, and 
    enjoy a dispensation of light and liberty. Let us be thankful for our 
    privilege, and "stand fast in the liberty with which Christ has made us 
    free."</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">2. What spirituality of mind we should possess!</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">Our superior privileges doubtless demand a correspondent 
    pre-eminence in our spirit and conduct. If we are "no longer servants, but 
    sons," we ought to manifest a filial affection towards God, and a delight in 
    his service. But do not many of the pious Jews reproach us? O let us walk 
    worthy of our high calling, and show forth the praises of him who has called 
    us out of darkness into his marvelous light! <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Pet%202.9" data-reference="1 Pet 2.9" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Peter 2:9</a>.</p>
    <p align="justify">&nbsp;</p>
    <font color="#ff0000"><b>
    <p align="justify">#2180</p>
    <p align="justify">HOLDING THE HEAD</p>
    <p align="justify"><a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Col%202.18-19" data-reference="Col 2.18-19" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Colossians 2:18-19</a> </p>
    </b></font>
    <p align="justify">"Do not let anyone who delights in false humility and the 
    worship of angels disqualify you for the prize. Such a person goes into 
    great detail about what he has seen, and his unspiritual mind puffs him up 
    with idle notions. He has lost connection with the Head, from whom the whole 
    body, supported and held together by its ligaments and sinews, grows as God 
    causes it to grow." </p>
    <p align="justify">WHILE the Apostles were yet in the full exercise of their 
    ministry, all manner of heresies sprang up in the Church. </p>
    <p align="justify">The <i>Jewish </i>converts brought with them their 
    partiality for the Mosaic ritual, and insisted on the continued observance 
    of it. </p>
    <p align="justify">The <i>heathen </i>converts introduced the dogmas of 
    their philosophy; on which they insisted, as rendering Christianity more 
    conformable with the opinions to which they had been accustomed. </p>
    <p align="justify">Hence the Apostle Paul, in the chapter before us, 
    repeatedly cautioned the Colossian saints against both the one and the other 
    of these heretical deceivers. "Beware," says he, "lest any man spoil you 
    through philosophy and vain deceit, after the tradition of men, after the 
    rudiments of the world, and not after Christ, verse 8." Again, "Therefore do 
    not let anyone judge you by what you eat or drink, or with regard to a 
    religious festival, a New Moon celebration or a Sabbath day. These are a 
    shadow of the things that were to come; the reality, however, is found in 
    Christ. verse 16, 17." And then, in reference to both the characters, he 
    says, "Do not let anyone who delights in false humility and the worship of 
    angels disqualify you for the prize. Such a person goes into great detail 
    about what he has seen, and his unspiritual mind puffs him up with idle 
    notions. He has lost connection with the Head." It seems that some of the 
    Jewish converts were inclined to rely on angels, as their mediators with 
    God; for God having employed them in the dispensation of his law, they 
    thought it probable that he would make use of them as his instruments also 
    in communicating the blessings of the Gospel. With the heathen converts, the 
    idea of an intermediate kind of deity was quite familiar; and, consequently, 
    coalescing easily with the Jewish teachers in their veneration of angels, 
    they formed, in the Church, a party, which it required all the zeal and 
    authority of the Apostle to suppress. It was to counteract their influence 
    that the Apostle suggested, in the words of my text,</p>
    <font color="#0000ff"><b>
    <p align="justify">I. A solemn caution not to depart from Christ—</p>
    </b></font>
    <p align="justify">It is here taken for granted, that Christians are all 
    united to Christ by faith, as their living Head. But the Apostle declared, 
    that the persons who were thus endeavoring to subvert the faith of the 
    Colossians did not hold Christ as their Head; and that to embrace their 
    opinions should, in effect, be to renounce Christ. </p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">This was true with respect to them at that time—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">To worship angels, and employ them as mediators with God, 
    was indeed proposed under an idea of "humility;" since it was supposed that 
    it would be presumptuous in man to apply directly to God, except through the 
    intervention of some creatures of a higher stamp and order; but if they came 
    to him through them as their mediators, they could not then fail of 
    obtaining the Divine favor. But while this was recommended as an indication 
    of humility, it proceeded, in fact, from nothing but pride: for, by 
    "intruding into things which they had not seen," and presuming to go beyond 
    what God had revealed, they showed that they were "vainly puffed up by their 
    fleshly mind." In recommending the adoption of these opinions, they did 
    eventually "rob men of their reward," instead of securing it to them by any 
    additional bonds. </p>
    <p align="justify">In truth, they did not themselves "hold fast to the 
    Head," the Lord Jesus Christ; and, so far as they prevailed, they actually 
    severed persons from Christ; and thereby ruined their immortal souls.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">And it is equally true with respect to many at this time—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">The whole Romish Church sanctions the worshiping both of 
    saints and angels: and, not content with having Christ as their mediator, 
    they make use of the Virgin Mary as their intercessor; and place as much 
    confidence in her, as in the Lord Jesus Christ himself. Need I say, what is 
    the origin of this, or what its effect will be? It is recommended under a 
    pretense of "humility:" but it is the offspring of pride and carnality; it 
    is recommended in order to secure the reward of Heaven; but it beguiles of 
    that reward all who embrace so fatal a system.</p>
    <p align="justify">And what are they better, who require some internal 
    qualifications in us, as a warrant for us to apply to Christ? The Papists 
    commend new mediators to us, in order to our obtaining of acceptance with 
    Christ; and these other deceivers require new qualifications in us for the 
    same end. And these, no less than the former, go beyond the Scriptures, 
    requiring of us what God himself has never required. </p>
    <p align="justify">All the qualification which God requires for our approach 
    to Christ is that we thirst after him, and be willing to accept his offered 
    benefits: "If any man thirst, let him come unto me and drink;" and "Whoever 
    will, let him come and take of the water of life freely." The substitution 
    of any other terms, whatever men may pretend, is the fruit of pride: for it 
    is an avowal, that we look for mercy at his hand as the reward of some kind 
    or degree of goodness in ourselves; and, in effect, it transfers a portion 
    at least of his glory to ourselves. It denies the entire freeness of divine 
    grace, and makes salvation in part to be of works. The consequence of this 
    will be that all who are thus led to renounce their hold of Christ, must 
    perish. They are beguiled of their reward, and betrayed to their everlasting 
    ruin.</p>
    <p align="justify">To this solemn caution is annexed,</p>
    <b><font color="#0000ff">
    <p align="justify">II. A most urgent reason for adhering to him—</p>
    </font>
    <p align="justify">It is by union with the Lord Jesus Christ that the whole 
    Church exists—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">There is the same union between Christ and his Church as 
    there is between the head and members of the natural body. From the head the 
    vital spirits may be said to flow throughout the whole body: nourishing 
    every part, diffusing strength throughout the whole system, and combining 
    all the members, so as to call forth and concentrate their respective 
    offices for the good of the whole. </p>
    <p align="justify">Thus it is that all the members of Christ's mystical body 
    receive life and strength from him: all are fitted for the discharge of 
    their several duties: all are made to possess one common interest, and to 
    act for one common end. There is not one life in the head, and another in 
    the members: it is one life that pervades them all: and this, too, in the 
    mystical body of Christ, no less than in our own natural body. It is "not we 
    that live, but Christ that lives in us, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Gal%202.20" data-reference="Gal 2.20" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Galatians 2:20</a>;" yes, "Christ 
    himself is our life, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Col%203.4" data-reference="Col 3.4" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Colossians 3:4</a>;" and by his continued agency within us, 
    we "increase with the increase of God."</p>
    <p align="justify">What then must be the result, if we are cut off from him? 
    We perish of necessity, as the members when severed from the head. Is this, 
    then, no reason why we would guard against the introduction of error, 
    especially of such errors as will have the effect of separating us from him?</p>
    <p align="justify">But we may further observe, that,</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">It is by union with Christ that the whole work of grace 
    is carried on in the soul of every believer—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">As there is "a body of sin, called the old man," in us by 
    nature, so is there "a new man" in us by grace: and all the different 
    graces, of which this new man consists, are nourished by the same divine 
    principle; and either decline or grow together, according as this is 
    communicated to us, or withheld. A man may have in his natural body a 
    greater measure of force and vigor in some one organ or member than in 
    others: the eye, the ear, the hand, the foot, may possess some appropriate 
    and distinguished excellence. But whatever affects the system generally, 
    must affect the body in every part, and produce a corresponding diminution 
    or increase of its powers. Now, if our connection with the Lord Jesus Christ 
    is kept close, and our communications from him abound, we shall have all our 
    graces lively, and vigorous, and active: but if there is anything to 
    intercept the communications of his grace, every grace will languish and 
    decay.</p>
    <p align="justify">Say, then, whether in this view also we are not concerned 
    with all care and diligence to "hold fast the Head?" Whether we consider the 
    interests of the Church collectively, or the welfare of every individual 
    believer, there does appear a necessity to watch against any interruption of 
    our union with Christ, and to seek from him incessant supplies of grace and 
    strength: for "through him we can do all things, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Phil%204.13" data-reference="Phil 4.13" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Philippians 4:13</a>;" but 
    "without him we can do nothing, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/John%2015.5" data-reference="John 15.5" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">John 15:5</a>."</p>
    <b><font color="#0000ff">
    <p align="justify">Behold from hence,</p>
    </font>
    <p align="justify">1. How wonderfully simple is the Gospel of Christ!</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">If we enter into the deep mysteries of religion in an 
    abstract way, the wisest and most acute are soon out of their depth: but if 
    we take them as represented by Scripture images, the weakest and most 
    ignorant Christian has as clear a conception of them as the most learned in 
    the universe. The connection between the head and the body, and the 
    dependence of the members on the head, may be more scientifically described 
    by a learned man; but they are not a whit more justly apprehended by him, 
    than by the poorest of mankind. Yet does this image contain the whole of 
    vital Christianity; which consists in this one thing, "a life of faith in 
    the Son of God, as having loved us, and given himself for us."</p>
    <p align="justify">Beloved brethren, take with you this image: conceive of 
    the Lord Jesus Christ as your head, from whom all vital influence proceeds. 
    Look to him for a communication of that influence to your soul. Bear in 
    mind, that, except as aided by power from him, you can do no more than your 
    members could if separated from your head. Remember, that as every member of 
    your body is alike under the influence of your head, so must every 
    disposition of your soul be under the control and influence of Christ! And, 
    as there is no schism in the body, no member affecting independence, or 
    living regardless of the head, so let there be no lack of attention to any 
    individual grace; but go to Him for a supply of all, that all may be 
    strengthened, and that you may grow up in all things into Christ, your 
    living head. Let your wisdom, your righteousness, your sanctification, your 
    complete redemption, be all viewed as in him, and all be derived continually 
    from him, according to the measure of the gift which he sees fit to impart.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">2. The danger of departing from it in the least degree—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">The persons who proposed the worshiping of angels did not 
    mean to renounce Christ; and had they been told that their conceit was in 
    reality a separation of themselves from him, they would have denied that any 
    such consequences could follow. And so it is when persons are looking for 
    some goodness of their own whereon to found their hope, or to warrant their 
    application to Christ; they have as little idea of the evil which they 
    commit, or of the consequences that must ensue. </p>
    <p align="justify">But remember, that <i>self </i>must he altogether 
    renounced; must be renounced by us, as much as it must by the fallen angels, 
    if salvation were at this moment offered to them. <i>All that we ever can 
    have, is in Christ: it is treasured up in him for our use, and must be 
    received from him. </i>There is nothing which must not be "received out of 
    his fullness:" and, if you will not come to him for it, you must inevitably 
    and eternally perish. He is a jealous God: he will not admit of rivals: he 
    will not endure that his glory would in any respect or degree be given to 
    another. Whatever, therefore, any man may pretend, or whatever specious 
    appearance any sentiment may assume, whether of superior wisdom, or deeper 
    humility, or more ardent zeal—admit nothing, for one moment, that may 
    interfere with the honor of the Lord Jesus: but be contented to receive all 
    from him, to depend altogether upon him, and to give him the glory of all 
    that you either receive or do. </p>
    <p align="justify">In a word, be to him what your members are to your head. 
    This idea is extremely simple. Allow nothing to set it aside, or to 
    interfere with it. Carry it into effect in your daily life and conduct: and 
    fear not, but that if you glorify him in this world, you shall be glorified 
    with him in the world above.</p>
    <p align="justify">&nbsp;</p>
    <font color="#ff0000"><b>
    <p align="justify">#2181</p>
    <p align="justify">Our Resurrection with Christ a Motive to 
    Heavenly-mindedness</p>
    <p align="justify"><a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Col%203.1" data-reference="Col 3.1" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Colossians 3:1</a></p>
    </b></font>
    <p align="justify">"If you then are risen with Christ, seek those things 
    which are above, where Christ sits on the right hand of God."</p>
    <p align="justify">ONE of the most distinguished peculiarities of our holy 
    religion is that it suggests entirely new motives to action. The inducements 
    which reason could offer, were (as all antiquity proves) altogether weak and 
    inefficient. Those alone which Christianity proposes are capable of 
    restraining the passions of men, and of regulating their conduct. Beg of God 
    then that you may feel the power of his word, while I set before you,</p>
    <font color="#0000ff"><b>
    <p align="justify">I. The duty here inculcated—</p>
    </b></font>
    <p align="justify">I by no means am intimating that we are at liberty to 
    neglect our earthly concerns. Circumstanced as we are, we must of necessity 
    devote much time and labor to the pursuit of worldly things: and, if we 
    neglected them, we would offend against the order of Divine Providence, who 
    has said in reference to them, "Six days shall you labor." But,</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">"The things which are above" are most worthy of our 
    pursuit—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">Among these we must number the favor of our offended God, 
    the manifestations of his love to our souls, the attainment of his image, 
    and the possession of his glory.</p>
    <p align="justify">Which of these things can be dispensed with? Or which can 
    be attained by a mere inactive wish, or by a formal and faint endeavor? 
    These things, in point of value and importance, as far excel all earthly 
    things, as the splendor of the meridian sun eclipses the faint radiance of 
    the glow-worm.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">These therefore we are to seek with our whole hearts—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">They are to have the first place in our esteem, and to be 
    sought with a diligence proportioned to their value, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Matt%206.33" data-reference="Matt 6.33" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Matthew 6:33</a>. Seeking 
    only will not suffice: we must <i>strive </i>to enter in at the strait gate; 
    for we are told that "many shall seek, and not be able, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Luke%2013.24" data-reference="Luke 13.24" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Luke 13:24</a>." "The 
    kingdom of Heaven must be taken by violence, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Matt%2011.12" data-reference="Matt 11.12" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Matthew 11:12</a>," even by the 
    holy violence of faith and prayer. </p>
    <p align="justify">The things above must be sought with the same constancy 
    and zeal as are employed by the world in the pursuit of things below. 
    Worldly men are never weary in the pursuit of their objects. From the 
    earliest dawn to the very hour when they retire to rest, their appetite for 
    earthly things continues; nor, whatever they may attain, are they ever 
    satisfied. Their energies may be enfeebled by labor; but their taste is 
    still the same: they savor the things which pertain to time and sense, 
    <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Rom%208.5" data-reference="Rom 8.5" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Romans 8:5</a>. They seek them constantly, them supremely, them only. </p>
    <p align="justify">Now this is the way in which we should "seek the things 
    that are above:" and, in comparison with these, all earthly things would be 
    to us as dung and dross. Even life itself would be of no value, if by 
    sacrificing it our eternal interests may be improved, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Luke%2014.26-27" data-reference="Luke 14.26-27" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Luke 14:26-27</a>; <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Luke%2014.33" data-reference="Luke 14.33" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Luke 
    14:33</a>.</p>
    <p align="justify">If this appears "a hard saying," attend while I lay 
    before you,</p>
    <font color="#0000ff"><b>
    <p align="justify">II. The considerations with which it is enforced—</p>
    </b></font>
    <p align="justify">The Apostle urges upon us our duty on the ground of 
    consistency. Mark,</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">1. Your professions—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">The word "If" does not express any doubt in the Apostle's 
    mind, but imports an acknowledged fact, namely, that the Christian is risen 
    with Christ. It is the same as if he had said, "Since you are risen with 
    Christ." Now every Christian is risen with Christ both federally, and 
    spiritually. Christ is his federal Head and Representative: and all that He 
    experienced, we experienced in him. Was he circumcised when a child? Was he 
    at the close of life crucified, dead, and buried? Did he rise, and ascend to 
    Heaven? And is he now sitting at the right hand of God? In the whole of this 
    we had, not an interest only, but a direct participation, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Col%202.10-12" data-reference="Col 2.10-12" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Colossians 
    2:10-12</a>.</p>
    <p align="justify">Exactly as we died in Adam, partaking, as it were, with 
    him in the sin which, as our head and representative, he committed, so all 
    which Christ did and suffered is imputed to us, as though we had ourselves 
    done and suffered it in him, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Cor%2015.22" data-reference="1 Cor 15.22" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Corinthians 15:22</a>. <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/2%20Cor%205.21" data-reference="2 Cor 5.21" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2 Corinthians 5:21</a>. </p>
    <p align="justify">Spiritually also are we risen in Christ. All that he did 
    and suffered is, if I may so speak, accomplished personally in every one of 
    us, his corporeal acts and sufferings being the model of what we experience 
    in our souls. This is by Paul stated with great accuracy. In his prayer for 
    the Ephesian Church, he desires that they may "know what is the exceeding 
    greatness of God's power in all his believing people, according to the 
    working of his mighty power, which he wrought in Christ, when he raised him 
    from the dead, and set him at his own right hand in the heavenly places."
    </p>
    <p align="justify">And then he marks distinctly and separately the work 
    which God accomplishes in his people, quickening them from the dead, raising 
    them up to newness of life, and setting them together in heavenly places in 
    Christ Jesus, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Eph%201.19-20" data-reference="Eph 1.19-20" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ephesians 1:19-20</a> with 2:4-6."</p>
    <p align="justify">Now then I ask, Is not this what as Christians you 
    profess? Do you not profess to be thus risen with Christ, savingly 
    interested in all that he did and suffered for you, and bound to be 
    conformed to him in the whole of this his mediatorial work and office. You 
    do profess it, whether you intend it or not. And <i>this profession binds 
    you to an entire devotedness of heart and life to God</i>. You must of 
    necessity "thus judge, that if One died for all, then were all dead; and 
    that he died for all, that those who live would not henceforth live unto 
    themselves, but unto him who died for them, and rose again, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/2%20Cor%205.14-15" data-reference="2 Cor 5.14-15" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2 Corinthians 
    5:14-15</a>."</p>
    <p align="justify">But you shall see this on authority that cannot be 
    disputed, and actually urged in the very way suggested by my text. "What 
    shall we say then; Shall we continue in sin that grace may abound? God 
    forbid! How shall we who are dead to sin (as we all profess to be) live any 
    longer therein? Don't you know, that as many of us as were baptized into 
    Jesus Christ, were baptized into his death? Therefore we are buried with him 
    by baptism into death; that like as Christ was raised from the dead by the 
    glory of the Father, even so we also would walk in newness of life <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Rom%206.1-11" data-reference="Rom 6.1-11" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Romans 
    6:1-11</a>."</p>
    <p align="justify">The point then is proved. Consistency requires that you 
    would seek primarily and with your whole hearts the things above.</p>
    <p align="justify">If yet you entertain a doubt of this, I ask you, what 
    judgment you yourselves pass on a carnal, sensual, worldly-minded professor 
    of religion? Do you not condemn him as inconsistent? Then in so doing you 
    pass judgment on yourselves.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">2. Your expectations—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">The words, "Where Christ sits at the right hand of God," 
    are not added casually and without design: they give exceeding great weight 
    and emphasis to all that precedes. These words express the expectations of 
    the Christian, as the former do his professions. "Christ is at the right 
    hand of God," the seat of honor and of power. But he is not there as a mere 
    individual for his own happiness only. He is there prosecuting still the 
    work which he began on earth, and in which we are as much savingly 
    interested as we are in what he did and suffered here below. </p>
    <p align="justify">We look to him to afford us all needful aid by the 
    constant supplies of his Spirit and grace, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/John%2016.7-11" data-reference="John 16.7-11" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">John 16:7-11</a>. <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/2%20Cor%2012.8-9" data-reference="2 Cor 12.8-9" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2 Corinthians 
    12:8-9</a>." </p>
    <p align="justify">We look to him to obtain for us the acceptance of our 
    poor imperfect services, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Pet%202.5" data-reference="1 Pet 2.5" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Peter 2:5</a>. </p>
    <p align="justify">We look to Him to come again and take us in due season to 
    a full participation of all the glory which he himself possesses, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/John%2016.23" data-reference="John 16.23" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">John 
    16:23</a>; <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/John%2017.24" data-reference="John 17.24" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">John 17:24</a>, and <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Rev%203.21" data-reference="Rev 3.21" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Revelation 3:21</a>. </p>
    <p align="justify">But in which of these shall we succeed, it we do not live 
    unto him? If we were to tell you, that a worldly and carnal life was the way 
    to obtain these blessings, would you not cry out against us as "blind 
    leaders of the blind?" Then behold what your expectations are, and how 
    powerfully they proclaim and enforce your duties. If "your faith and hope 
    depend altogether upon the exaltation of Christ to the right hand of God, 1 
    Peter 1:21," your duty must of necessity be to look to him continually, that 
    you may receive out of his fullness all that your necessities require.</p>
    <b><font color="#0000ff">
    <p align="justify">And now see,</p>
    </font>
    <p align="justify">1. How few real Christians there are upon earth—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">If they were Christians who sought only the things below, 
    there would be no lack of them in every place. </p>
    <p align="justify">But if those only are Christians who in heart and life 
    are risen with Christ, and who seek only the things above, then are they few 
    indeed. </p>
    <p align="justify">Brethren, try yourselves by these marks, and you shall 
    soon find your real character before God: But know this of a truth, that, 
    whatever you may think to the contrary, they only who live unto Christ in 
    this world, shall ever live with him in the world to come.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">2. How blessed are those who are Christians indeed—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">Being risen with Christ, their lives are hidden with 
    Christ in God, beyond the reach of men or devils, verse 3. While they are 
    engaged in heavenly pursuits, they may enjoy the security which God has 
    ordained for them. Oppositions, indeed, and difficulties they must expect; 
    but Christ will not lose one member of his mystical body. He derides the 
    vain attempts of his enemies and ours. We too may defy the confederate 
    powers of earth and Hell, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Rom%208.33-34" data-reference="Rom 8.33-34" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Romans 8:33-34</a>; for, however they may obtain a 
    temporary triumph, their efforts shall terminate in their own confusion. 
    With Christ we shall rise victorious; and "when he who is our life shall 
    appear, then shall we also appear with him in glory! verse 4."</p>
    <p align="justify">&nbsp;</p>
    <font color="#ff0000"><b>
    <p align="justify">#2182</p>
    <p align="justify">HEAVENLY-MINDEDNESS</p>
    <p align="justify"><a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Col%203.2" data-reference="Col 3.2" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Colossians 3:2</a></p>
    </b></font>
    <p align="justify">"Set your affections on things above, not on things on 
    the earth."</p>
    <p align="justify">IT seems harsh and paradoxical to say that Christianity 
    is very imperfectly understood among us. Respecting its mysterious <i>
    doctrines</i>, perhaps, the allegation would be admitted without difficulty: 
    but respecting its <i>precepts</i>, scarcely anyone would suspect that the 
    observation could have any foundation in truth. But it is to the preceptive 
    part especially that I intend the remark to be applied: and I think that 
    before I have closed my present subject, the greater part of you will agree 
    with me, that the sentiment is just. </p>
    <p align="justify">The <i>morality </i>of Christians in general goes only to 
    the conduct of men so far as it is visible to those around us. But <i>the 
    Christian precepts extend to the inmost feelings of the soul, and requires a 
    conformity to the Savior himself</i>, not only in the dispositions of his 
    mind while he sojourned upon earth, but in the change wrought upon him in 
    his exaltation to Heaven: it requires us to be dead to sin as truly as ever 
    he died for sin; and to live as truly and entirely to God as he did, and yet 
    does, in his risen state in glory. The precept which you have just heard 
    will fitly illustrate this truth. I will endeavor to mark,</p>
    <font color="#0000ff"><b>
    <p align="justify">I. Its import—</p>
    </b></font>
    <p align="justify">Directions in Scripture are often put in a way of 
    contrast, when they are to be understood only in a way of comparison. Such, 
    for instance, is the declaration, "I will have mercy, and not sacrifice." We 
    are not to understand that passage as prohibiting sacrifices, which had been 
    expressly enjoined, and were yet of necessity to be offered; but only as 
    expressing an approbation of acts of mercy, even though they would supersede 
    the observance of some positive injunction. </p>
    <p align="justify">When our Lord says, "Labor not for the food that 
    perishes, but for the food that endures unto everlasting life," he must not 
    be understood as discouraging an attention to worldly business: for God has 
    authoritatively commanded, "Six days shall you labor." It is in a 
    comparative sense only that his words must be understood: and in the same 
    manner must we interpret also the words before us. Mark,</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">1. The things here contrasted—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">"The things which are on earth" are those which relate to 
    this present life. Even intellectual pursuits must be included, no less than 
    the pleasures, or riches, or honors, of the world. </p>
    <p align="justify">On the other hand, by "the things which are above," we 
    must understand everything relating to the soul, its first acceptance with 
    God, its progressive restoration to the Divine image, and its final 
    possession of the heavenly glory. The latter of these we are to pursue, if 
    not exclusively—yet supremely, so as to show that they have no rival 
    whatever in our souls.</p>
    <p align="justify">The term here translated "Set your <i>affections </i>on 
    things above," is more literally rendered, in the margin, "<i>Mind </i>the 
    things that are above." The term imports, not an exercise of the 
    intellectual powers only, but also of the will and the affections; and such 
    an exercise of them as demonstrates the supreme attachment of the soul. 
    Perhaps it was on this account that our translators preferred the 
    translation; which, though less proper in itself, more exactly conveyed the 
    sense to those who were unacquainted with the original. But, not to separate 
    the words, let us take them in their collective import; and consider,</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">2. The precept relating to them—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">I have said that all concern about earthly things is not 
    forbidden: on the contrary, there are many things which require an ardor and 
    intensity in the pursuit, and cannot be attained without. But they must not 
    engage the affections of the soul; they must not be permitted to stand in 
    competition with Heaven and heavenly things. </p>
    <p align="justify">In comparison with the knowledge of Christ, all that the 
    world contains must be in our eyes no better than "dung and dross." The 
    favor of an offended God: <br>
    the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ in all its sanctifying operations; <br>
    the witness of the Holy Spirit testifying of our adoption into his family, 
    and of our interest in Christ; <br>
    and, finally, the eternal possession of his glory.</p>
    <p align="justify">What deserves to be sought after, like these? </p>
    <p align="justify">What will bear any comparison with these? </p>
    <p align="justify">These, then, are to occupy our supreme regard; and 
    everything else must give way to them. Earthly satisfactions of any kind, if 
    they stand in competition with them, must all be sacrificed without 
    hesitation and without regret. So permanent must be the ascendency of these 
    things in our minds, that no labor for them shall appear too great, and no 
    suffering too intense. In comparison with them, even life itself must be of 
    no value in our eyes, and the whole world be only as the small dust upon the 
    scale.</p>
    <p align="justify">This precept does indeed appear to impose a duty that is 
    quite impracticable: but, to show that it deserves our most attentive 
    regards, I will display,</p>
    <font color="#0000ff"><b>
    <p align="justify">II. Its reasonableness—</p>
    </b></font>
    <p align="justify">Let us take a more distinct survey of the two different 
    objects which are here contrasted; and the preference required in behalf of 
    heavenly things will be found precisely such as it befits us to manifest. 
    For,</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">1. They are more excellent in themselves—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">What is there truly valuable in the things of this world? 
    They have no intrinsic worth: they are only good as being high in the 
    estimation of men. <i>An angel would disregard them all, as much as we would 
    the dirt under our feet. Crowns, kingdoms, empires—what are they all, but 
    the baubles of children, which a man in his senses would despise!</i> Beyond 
    food and clothing there is nothing worth a thought: and they derive their 
    value, not from anything in themselves, but from the necessities of our 
    nature, which render them important in our eyes. </p>
    <p align="justify">But there is real excellency in: <br>
    the favor of God, <br>
    the grace of Christ, <br>
    the witness of the Spirit, <br>
    and the glory of Heaven! </p>
    <p align="justify">Yes, truly: these elevate our nature, and ennoble it, and 
    raise it to its primitive perfection and blessedness. These things the 
    highest angel in Heaven cannot but approve; yes, he must account them as 
    objects on which it is impossible to bestow too great, or too undivided, an 
    attention.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">2. They are more satisfactory to our minds—</p>
    </b><i>
    </i><p align="justify"><i>Those who possess the most of this world are the very 
    persons who most feel the emptiness and vanity of it all!</i> Go to those 
    who have attained all that their hearts could desire, and ask them whether 
    they have not grasped a shadow? A name, a title, a ribbon of distinction; 
    what contemptible things in comparison with those which belong to the soul! 
    Who that possesses them does not feel an aching void in his bosom, unless 
    with them he possesses also the favor of God? But the blessings of which we 
    have before spoken, are solid; and the person who enjoys them, possesses 
    rest in his soul. "Having drunk of the living waters, he thirsts no more" 
    for anything besides.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">3. They are more conducive to our happiness—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">Are the rich and great happier than other people? Not a 
    wit! A Lazarus, with God's love shed abroad in his heart, is happier than 
    the Rich Man among all his banquets. Search the Scriptures, and see whether 
    those who have reveled most in their wealth, and drunk most deeply of the 
    cup of pleasure—have not pronounced it all, not merely vanity, but vexation 
    of spirit also? </p>
    <p align="justify">But look at the possessors of spiritual good: take them 
    in their lowest state; view them poor, and weeping, and mourning, and 
    hungering and thirsting after degrees of holiness unattained: what says the 
    Scripture respecting them? What? Our Savior himself declares them "blessed," 
    "blessed," "blessed," "blessed!" If, like Paul and Silas, they are reduced 
    to the most pitiable condition that can be conceived, they have ample ground 
    for the most exalted joy: and even in martyrdom itself they have no cause 
    for anything but thanksgiving and praise.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">4. They are more easily to be attained—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">Multitudes, however much they were to labor, could never 
    gain earthly distinction: and multitudes who do labor for it with a 
    reasonable hope of success, are left a prey to the most painful 
    disappointments. But who that has the heart of a man is incapable of 
    acquiring heavenly blessings? Or who ever failed in attaining them, provided 
    he only sought them in humility and faith? Methinks this is one of the chief 
    excellencies of spiritual things, that they are open alike to all, and never 
    are sought in vain. Of them, in all their fullness, we may say, "Everyone 
    who asks receives; and he who seeks, finds; and to him who knocks, it shall 
    be opened."</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">5. They are more lasting—</p>
    </b><i>
    </i><p align="justify"><i>Let a man possess the whole world—how long shall he 
    retain it? Every moment his happiness is drawing nearer to a close! </i>No 
    sooner is the breath departed from his body, than he surrenders it all to 
    some new possessor, who shall, like him also, retain it but a little time. 
    For "we can carry nothing away with us when we die," we came naked into the 
    world, and naked must we depart from it. </p>
    <p align="justify">But is it thus with the man who has sought his happiness 
    in God? No, truly; "he has treasures in Heaven;" and at death he goes to the 
    full possession of them. <i>His happiness, instead of being terminated at 
    death, is then consummated! </i>He then, as it were, comes of age, and 
    enters on the full possession of "his inheritance, which is incorruptible 
    and undefiled, and fades not away, reserved in Heaven for him."</p>
    <p align="justify">And now let me ask, Is it unreasonable that these things 
    would occupy your minds, in preference to the vanities of time and sense? 
    These things, which are:<br>
    so excellent in themselves, <br>
    so satisfactory to us, <br>
    so conducive to our happiness, <br>
    so certain to be attained, and <br>
    so lasting in the enjoyment? </p>
    <p align="justify">Surely the poor empty vanities of time and sense cannot 
    for a moment, stand in competition with these; nor do they deserve so much 
    as a thought, in comparison with them.</p>
    <b><font color="#0000ff">
    <p align="justify">Let me now commend this precept to you,</p>
    </font>
    <p align="justify">1. As a test to try your character—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">In this view it is particularly set before us by Paul: 
    "Those who are of the flesh, mind the things after the flesh; but those who 
    are after the Spirit, mind the things of the Spirit, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Rom%208.5" data-reference="Rom 8.5" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Romans 8:5</a>." Now, here 
    the very same term is used as in our text: and it forms a line of 
    distinction between the carnal and the spiritual man, between "him who is in 
    a state of death, and him who is in the enjoyment of life and peace, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Rom%208.5" data-reference="Rom 8.5" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Romans 
    8:5</a>." It may be thought, indeed, that the adoption of evangelical opinions, 
    and the making an open profession of piety, will supersede this test: but 
    nothing can ever set it aside. </p>
    <p align="justify">The Philippian converts judged that they were in a state 
    of acceptance with God, because they professed faith in Christ. But 
    respecting many of them, Paul said, "Many walk, of whom I have told you 
    often, and tell you now even weeping, that they are the enemies of the cross 
    of Christ, whose end is destruction!" And then, assigning the reasons for 
    his judgment, he combines with other things this charge, "<i>They mind 
    earthly things! </i><a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Phil%203.18-19" data-reference="Phil 3.18-19" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Philippians 3:18-19</a>." </p>
    <p align="justify">I call every one of you, then, to try yourselves by this 
    infallible mark. It is a point easily ascertained. <i>You need only examine 
    your lives from day to day, and see what it is that interests you most, and 
    forms the leading objects of your pursuit.</i> You may be deeply engaged 
    about earthly things, and yet be right in the sight of God, provided 
    heavenly things are regarded by you with supreme and paramount affection. 
    Bring then, I beg you, this matter to a trial; and never cease to implore of 
    God that spiritual discernment which he alone can give, and that uprightness 
    of heart which is indispensable to the forming of a right judgment.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">2. As a rule, to regulate your conduct—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">Truly, this must distinguish every child of God: though
    <i>in </i>the world, we must not be <i>of </i>it: "our hearts and minds must 
    be in Heaven." This is our duty, our honor, our happiness, our security. 
    There is no standing still in religion. If we advance not, we recede. Be not 
    contented to rest in a low state, but "press forward for the highest 
    attainments in holiness; forgetting all that is behind, and reaching forward 
    to that which is before, until you have fully attained the prize of your 
    high calling!"</p>
    <p align="justify">&nbsp;</p>
    <font color="#ff0000"><b>
    <p align="justify">#2183</p>
    <p align="justify">THE EXALTED STATE OF A CHRISTIAN</p>
    <p align="justify"><a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Col%203.3-4" data-reference="Col 3.3-4" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Colossians 3:3-4</a> </p>
    </b></font>
    <p align="justify">"For you died, and your life is now hidden with Christ in 
    God. When Christ, who is your life, appears, then you also will appear with 
    him in glory!" </p>
    <p align="justify">INNUMERABLE are the advantages which Scripture gives us 
    over the heathen philosophers: for, while it reveals to us a much sublimer 
    rule of conduct than they were able to devise, it affords motives sufficient 
    to incline us to duty, and teaches us where to obtain strength for the 
    performance of it. <i>The duty it enjoins is nothing less than a supreme 
    delight in heavenly things</i>; but at the same time it animates us by the 
    consideration of the privileges we enjoy and the prospects we have in view. 
    What the Christian possesses in these respects may be seen in the words 
    before us, in which we notice,</p>
    <font color="#0000ff"><b>
    <p align="justify">I. His exalted state—</p>
    </b></font>
    <p align="justify">The Christian is a paradox, being both dead and living at 
    the same time. </p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">He is "dead"—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">Once he was alive wholly and entirely to legal hopes and 
    carnal enjoyments: but now is dead to both. He now sees that he has no 
    righteousness of his own for his justification before God, and no strength 
    of his own for the fulfillment of God's holy will. He therefore renounces 
    all dependence on himself, and seeks righteousness and strength in Christ 
    alone, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Isa%2045.24" data-reference="Isa 45.24" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Isaiah 45:24</a>.</p>
    <i>
    </i><p align="justify"><i>As for the enjoyment of the things of time and sense, he 
    has the same capacity for it as ever; but he has lost his inclination for 
    it, and no longer seeks his happiness in it.</i> He feels the emptiness and 
    vanity of all sublunary good: and, while he is thankful for the portion of 
    it that is committed to him, he regards the whole world as an object that is 
    crucified, and is himself crucified unto it! <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Gal%206.14" data-reference="Gal 6.14" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Galatians 6:14</a>.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">Yet is he "alive" in a far higher sense than ever he was 
    before—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">He has in Christ a "life," whereby he is enabled to live 
    unto his God, and to walk in the paths of holiness and peace. This life is 
    "hidden with Christ in God;" so that, while the world sees it not, Satan is 
    not able to destroy it. When Adam had life, so to speak, in his own 
    possession, his great adversary prevailed over him and slew him: the 
    believer therefore is placed beyond the reach of Satan's efforts, and has 
    his life treasured up in Heaven, where Satan has no access, and in God, over 
    whom he can have no power.</p>
    <p align="justify">Indeed Christ himself lives in the believer <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Gal%202.20" data-reference="Gal 2.20" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Galatians 
    2:20</a>, and is "his very life." What the soul is to the body, that is Christ 
    to the believer's soul, acting in all its faculties, and operating in all 
    its energies. And hence the believer, however dead he is in himself, is 
    enabled to live in a way that no other creature in the universe can live.</p>
    <p align="justify">But the believer must be yet further viewed by us in,</p>
    <b><font color="#0000ff">
    <p align="justify">II. His glorious expectations—</p>
    </font>
    <p align="justify">The Savior, though once as unknown by the world as they, 
    and still more despised, shall one day appear again in glory!</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">The time is fast approaching, when he shall descend from 
    Heaven in his own glory, and in the glory of his Father and his holy angels. 
    While he was upon earth, his glory was, for the most part, veiled. A little 
    of it sinned forth on Mount Tabor; and his own more immediate followers 
    "beheld somewhat of his glory, as the glory of the only-begotten of the 
    Father." But "the world knew him not," "the darkness could not apprehend his 
    light." But in the day of judgment his appearance will be such as becomes 
    his august character, so that he will be equally acknowledged by all, 
    whether friends or enemies, as "King of kings and Lord of lords!"</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">Then will the whole assembly of believers appear with him 
    in glory!</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">They will be gathered from every quarter of the globe "to 
    meet their Lord in the air," every one of them with "bodies like unto his 
    glorious body," and souls like unto his glorified soul; for they will be 
    altogether "like him, when they shall see him as he is! <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20John%203.2" data-reference="1 John 3.2" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 John 3:2</a>." They 
    will then appear:<br>
    as monuments of his grace, <br>
    as trophies of his victory, <br>
    as heirs of his glory! </p>
    <p align="justify">Truly he will be admired and glorified in them, when it 
    shall be seen what sovereignty he has exercised in the choice of them, and 
    what power he has put forth for their salvation! <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/2%20Thess%201.10" data-reference="2 Thess 1.10" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2 Thessalonians 1:10</a>. It 
    will then be seen, not that they triumphed, but that he triumphed <i>for </i>
    them, (upon his cross, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Col%201.15" data-reference="Col 1.15" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Colossians 1:15</a>,) and <i>over </i>them, (by his 
    converting grace, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Ps%2045.5" data-reference="Ps 45.5" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Psalm 45:5</a>. <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/2%20Cor%2010.5" data-reference="2 Cor 10.5" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2 Corinthians 10:5</a>,) and <i>in </i>them, by 
    the sanctifying efficacy of his Word and Spirit, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/John%2010.28" data-reference="John 10.28" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">John 10:28</a>; Then will they 
    be seated with him upon his throne, and as "joint-heirs with him" be 
    partakers of his kingdom for evermore!</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">Of this, the present state of their souls justifies an 
    assured expectation.</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">The connection between the two parts of my text must on 
    no account be overlooked. Both "the death" of the saints, and "their life" 
    warrant an assurance, that they shall reign with Christ in glory. Who can 
    hurt the soul of one that is dead? So neither can anyone destroy a soul that 
    is "dead to sin:" in both cases, the soul is hidden with Christ in God.</p>
    <p align="justify">Again, when our life was committed to the keeping of the 
    first Adam, he, though perfect, and in Paradise, allowed it to be wrested 
    from him by the subtlety of Satan. To prevent a recurrence of such a 
    calamity, our renewed life is not committed to our own care, but is 
    treasured up in the second Adam, and is hidden with Christ in God, out of 
    the reach of any enemy! </p>
    <p align="justify">Who then shall prevail against us? Not all the powers of 
    earth or Hell shall effect our ruin: "our life being hidden with Christ in 
    God," we are placed beyond the reach of evil; and therefore may be sure, 
    that when he shall appear again to judge the world, we also shall appear 
    with him in glory. This seems to be the true import of the passage; and 
    nothing less than this will adequately convey to our minds the security and 
    blessedness of a believing soul.</p>
    <b><font color="#0000ff">
    <p align="justify">ADDRESS—</p>
    </font>
    <p align="justify">1. Let believers be sensible of the <i>distinguished 
    mercy </i>given unto them—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">"Who is like unto you, O people saved by the Lord?" 
    Behold the unregenerate world: they are "dead," it is true; but to what are 
    they dead? Not to self, but to God and to everything that concerns the soul; 
    while you are dead to the law, and to sin, and to the world, and alive unto 
    God, through Jesus Christ. <i>Light and darkness are not more different from 
    each other, than is the spiritual from the natural man</i>; <i>and the 
    regenerate man from him who remains dead in trespasses and sins</i>. And who 
    has put the difference between you and the unbelieving world? Who has made 
    you children of God and heirs of glory—while so many millions of your 
    fellow-creatures have the wicked one for their father, and everlasting 
    misery as their portion! Truly, if you do not bless and adore your God, and 
    rend the air with your hosannahs, the very stones will cry out against you.
    </p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">2. Let them endeavor to <i>walk worthy </i>of their high 
    calling—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">This is the entire scope both of the preceding and the 
    following context. "Set your affections on things above," "for you are 
    dead," etc. Then after the text it is added, "Mortify therefore your members 
    upon earth." This should be the effect of all God's mercies to us: and I 
    call on every one who professes to have received life from Christ, to give 
    evidence of that life, by "walking in all things just as Christ walked".</p>
    <p align="justify">&nbsp;</p>
    <font color="#ff0000"><b>
    <p align="justify">#2184</p>
    <p align="justify">CHRIST IS ALL</p>
    <p align="justify"><a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Col%203.11" data-reference="Col 3.11" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Colossians 3:11</a></p>
    </b></font>
    <p align="justify">"Christ is all, and in all."</p>
    <p align="justify">MEN are ever ready to value themselves upon their natural 
    endowments, their civil distinctions, or their religious privileges; and to 
    imagine that a preeminence in these things gives them some kind of claim to 
    honor and respect, even from God himself. But nothing which a natural man 
    can possess, will give him any such advantage over others as shall entitle 
    him to boast, as though his salvation were in any measure of, or from, 
    himself. The most learned "Greek" must be indebted to divine teaching as 
    much as the unlettered "Scythian;" and the Jew that has been admitted into 
    covenant with God by "circumcision," be as much saved by the blood and 
    righteousness of Christ as an "uncircumcised" or idolatrous "barbarian;" the 
    "free-man" has no superiority above the "slave." All stand upon the same 
    footing with respect to salvation; all without exception are dependent upon 
    Christ for all their mercies: in all cases, relating to all persons, and to 
    all the circumstances of each, the creature is nothing, and Christ is all, 
    "he is all in all." We shall,</p>
    <font color="#0000ff"><b>
    <p align="justify">I. Illustrate this truth—</p>
    </b></font>
    <p align="justify">If we consult the Scriptures, or our own experience, 
    Christ will be found all in procuring, imparting, maintaining, and 
    completing our salvation.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">1. Christ is all in <i>procuring </i>our salvation—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">Who among the sons of men first suggested to our Lord the 
    plan of saving our ruined race through the sacrifice of himself? Who 
    assisted him in performing the mighty work which he had undertaken? "Did he 
    not tread the winepress of God's wrath alone? <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Isa%2063.3" data-reference="Isa 63.3" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Isaiah 63:3</a>." When he 
    "finished transgression, made an end of sin, made reconciliation for 
    iniquity, and brought in an everlasting righteousness," "there was none with 
    him;" "he looked and there was no man; therefore his own arm brought 
    salvation! <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Isa%2059.16" data-reference="Isa 59.16" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Isaiah 59:16</a>." </p>
    <p align="justify">Who can add to the work which he has accomplished? Who 
    can bring forth any works of supererogation or perfection that shall eke out 
    his righteousness, or give weight and efficacy to his sacrifice? Surely 
    Christ alone must be acknowledged as "the author of eternal salvation! 
    <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Heb%205.9" data-reference="Heb 5.9" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hebrews 5:9</a>."</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">2. Christ is all in <i>imparting </i>our salvation—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">The state of mankind may be fitly compared to the <i>dry 
    bones </i>in Ezekiel's vision, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Ezek%2037.1-3" data-reference="Ezek 37.1-3" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ezekiel 37:1-3</a>; they are altogether incapable 
    of exerting themselves in the way of godliness, or of performing the 
    functions of the spiritual life. He who commanded Lazarus to come forth from 
    the grave, and who calls himself "the resurrection and the life," must 
    quicken them, or they will remain to all eternity "dead in trespasses and 
    sins." If "we choose him, and love him, it is because he has first chosen 
    us, and loved us! <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Jer%2031.3" data-reference="Jer 31.3" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Jeremiah 31:3</a>. <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/John%2015.16" data-reference="John 15.16" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">John 15:16</a>." There is not a saint on earth 
    that must not say, "By the grace of God, I am what I am! <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Cor%2015.10" data-reference="1 Cor 15.10" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Corinthians 
    15:10</a>." "It is not of blood, or of the will of the flush, or of the will of 
    man, that we are born, but of God, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/John%201.13" data-reference="John 1.13" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">John 1:13</a>." Through the pride of our 
    hearts indeed, we are too apt to boast: but "who among us has anything which 
    he has not received, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/2%20Cor%204.7" data-reference="2 Cor 4.7" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2 Corinthians 4:7</a>." Who must not trace up to God both 
    his "disposition to will, and his ability to do" what is right and good? 
    <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Phil%202.13" data-reference="Phil 2.13" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Philippians 2:13</a>. Nothing but the most consummate pride can hinder us from 
    confessing that "salvation is, not of him who wills, or of him who runs, but 
    of God that shows mercy! <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Rom%209.16" data-reference="Rom 9.16" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Romans 9:16</a>;" and that, "if we have been saved and 
    called with a holy calling, it has not been according to our works, but 
    according to God's eternal purpose and grace! <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/2%20Tim%201.9" data-reference="2 Tim 1.9" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2 Timothy 1:9</a>."</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">3. Christ is all in <i>maintaining </i>our salvation—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">Nothing is more evident than our inability to maintain 
    our natural life: however careful we be in the use of means, we cannot 
    secure our <i>bodies </i>against the effects of disease or accident. The 
    preservation of our <i>spiritual </i>life is yet further beyond the reach of 
    our foresight or our skill. If left by God for one moment, we shall fall. If 
    Adam, even in Paradise, yielded to temptation, notwithstanding he was a 
    perfect man, then how much more shall we, who are full of evil? Paul 
    acknowledges that, notwithstanding all the grace he had received, he "had 
    not in himself a sufficiency even to think a good thought! <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/2%20Cor%203.5" data-reference="2 Cor 3.5" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2 Corinthians 
    3:5</a>." </p>
    <p align="justify">As water ceases to flow when its communication with the 
    fountain is cut off, or as light is instantly extinguished as soon as the 
    rays of the sun are intercepted, so all spiritual life would cease in us for 
    ever, if "Christ, who is our life, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Col%203.4" data-reference="Col 3.4" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Colossians 3:4</a>," would for one instant 
    withhold his quickening influence, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/John%2015.5" data-reference="John 15.5" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">John 15:5</a>. </p>
    <p align="justify">From hence it is that we are necessitated to "live 
    entirely by faith in the Son of God," and to "receive continually out of his 
    fullness, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Gal%202.20" data-reference="Gal 2.20" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Galatians 2:20</a>."</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">4. Christ is all in <i>completing </i>our salvation—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">While we continue in the body, we shall be as dependent 
    upon Christ for everything, as we have been at any period of our existence. 
    He who has been "the <i>author</i>, must also be the <i>finisher </i>of our 
    faith, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Heb%2012.2" data-reference="Heb 12.2" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hebrews 12:2</a>;" the same "Zerubbabel who laid the foundation of this 
    spiritual work, must finish it with his own hands, in order that, when the 
    head-stone shall be brought forth with shoutings, we may cry, Grace, grace 
    unto it forever! <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Zech%204.7-9" data-reference="Zech 4.7-9" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Zechariah 4:7-9</a>." Indeed, it is not only to the end of life 
    that Christ will carry on his work, but long after we have moldered in the 
    grave, "he will raise us up again at the last day! <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/John%206.39-40" data-reference="John 6.39-40" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">John 6:39-40</a>," appoint us 
    our proper portion, exalt us to his throne of glory, and be the continued 
    source of our happiness through all eternity! <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Rev%207.17" data-reference="Rev 7.17" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Revelation 7:17</a>; <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Rev%2021.23" data-reference="Rev 21.23" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Revelation 
    21:23</a>.</p>
    <p align="justify">This being a truth of infinite importance, we shall 
    endeavor to,</p>
    <font color="#0000ff"><b>
    <p align="justify">II. Improve it—</p>
    </b></font>
    <p align="justify">It is not a mere assent to this doctrine that will profit 
    our souls, but the application of it to our hearts and consciences. Let us 
    then apply it:</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">1. For reproof—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">In how strong a light does the guilt of <i>worldly men
    </i>appear when viewed through the medium of this truth! </p>
    <p align="justify">God assures us that no distinctions of whatever kind will 
    effectually make us happy; and that the happiness of all must be altogether 
    in, and through Christ.</p>
    <p align="justify">The worldling, on the contrary, declares, by his practice 
    at least, that the world, and not Christ, is the true source of rational 
    enjoyment. What is this but to "make God a liar?" and shall this be deemed a 
    light offense in the day of judgment? </p>
    <p align="justify">But this subject more particularly condemns the 
    self-righteous. These, instead of looking to Christ for the free, unmerited, 
    and continued exercise of his grace, are ready to boast that they are not as 
    other men, and to go forth in a dependence on their own strength and 
    goodness: instead of regarding him as their entire "wisdom, righteousness, 
    sanctification, and redemption," they transfer much of his glory to 
    themselves; instead of making him their all, they make him almost nothing. 
    Do such persons honor Christ? or can they expect to be honored by him before 
    the assembled universe? </p>
    <p align="justify">Even true <i>believers </i>will see much cause to be 
    ashamed when they reflect how low their thoughts of Christ have been, and 
    how cold their devoutest affections towards him are.</p>
    <p align="justify">Above all, the <i>ministers </i>of the Gospel, even the 
    most faithful among them, have reason to be ashamed. They know that they, 
    who neglect Christ, neglect their all; and that the consequences of that 
    neglect will be inexpressibly dreadful. Should not then their "eyes run down 
    with tears day and night for the pride" and ignorance of their people? 
    Should they not "beseech them," yes, and entreat God for them, with floods 
    of tears, if that by any means they might prevail on some to embrace the 
    Savior? Have they not reason to tremble lest the blood of multitudes who 
    perish would be required at their hands? Surely they, who are ready to 
    condemn their zeal, would rather pity them, and pray for them, and encourage 
    their activity to the utmost.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">2. For direction—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">They who are inquiring, what shall we do to be saved? 
    have here the shortest and plainest direction that can be given them: if 
    they remember that "Christ is all," and heartily endeavor to make him their 
    all, they can never perish. Their danger arises not less from their aversion 
    to exalt the Savior, than it does from the love of worldly and carnal lusts. 
    Yes, it is far easier to mortify any wicked habit whatever, than to bring 
    the soul to a sincere acquiescence in Christ as our all. We are always 
    wanting to retain some ground of self-preference, and self-delight: but, if 
    ever we be saved by him, we must lie in his hands as new-born infants, and 
    be contented to be "washed, justified, and sanctified by him" alone! 1 
    Corinthians 6:11.</p>
    <p align="justify">The drooping and doubting Christian may also find in 
    these words the very direction which he most of all stands in need of. 
    Doubts and fears arise, either from a defective view of Christ's 
    all-sufficiency, or from an apprehension of our own lack of fitness to 
    participate in his benefits. We wish to see ourselves purified in some 
    measure, in order that we may be warranted to lay hold on the promises: 
    whereas the Scripture teaches us, first to lay hold on the promises as 
    sinners, that "by them we may" become saints, and "cleanse ourselves from 
    all filthiness both of flesh and spirit, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/2%20Cor%207.1" data-reference="2 Cor 7.1" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2 Corinthians 7:1</a>." We mean not to 
    encourage sin of any kind; God forbid: but <i>we must go to Christ as having 
    nothing in ourselves, that in him we may have all</i>.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">3. For comfort—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">Doubtless, to those who determine to abide in sin, no 
    consolation whatever can be administered, for "the wrath of God does, and 
    ever will, abide upon them!" But to those who would forsake sin, though they 
    be now the very chief of sinners, our text affords unspeakable comfort. They 
    are not to heal themselves in part, and then to apply to the Physician; but 
    to go to Christ just as they are, and to cast themselves entirely upon him. 
    O that some might be encouraged to flee to him for refuge! For as he must be 
    all in the very best of men, so he is willing to be all to the vilest of the 
    human race: "him who goes unto him, he will never cast out!" </p>
    <p align="justify">As for the true believer, the subject before us is the 
    one ground of all his comfort: if Christ were not to be his all, he would 
    absolutely despair; because he knows that "without Christ he can do 
    nothing." But knowing also the all-sufficiency and faithfulness of Christ, 
    he commits himself cheerfully into his hands, "confident that he who has 
    begun the good work in him, will perform it to the end, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Phil%201.6" data-reference="Phil 1.6" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Philippians 1:6</a>," 
    and "preserve him blameless to his heavenly kingdom."</p>
    <p align="justify">&nbsp;</p>
    <font color="#ff0000"><b>
    <p align="justify">#2185</p>
    <p align="justify">THE IMPORTANCE OF SANCTIFICATION</p>
    <p align="justify"><a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Col%203.11" data-reference="Col 3.11" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Colossians 3:11</a></p>
    </b></font>
    <p align="justify">"Christ is all, and is in all!"</p>
    <p align="justify">The Author, in the preceding Discourse, has treated this 
    text as commentators in general have done, in reference to our <i>
    justification </i>before God. But he apprehends on further consideration, 
    that it refers rather to our <i>sanctification</i>. In either sense, the 
    position is true, that "Christ is all;" but the latter interpretation seems 
    more exactly to convey the mind of the Spirit in this passage. The reader, 
    by comparing the two Discourses, will be enabled to judge for himself.</p>
    <p align="justify">In order to ascertain the true sense of any passage of 
    Scripture, two things are to be attended to: </p>
    <p align="justify">we should mark the scope of the context, and </p>
    <p align="justify">compare the terms or phrases with similar passages of 
    Holy Writ. </p>
    <p align="justify">By separating these canons of interpretation, we shall 
    often overlook the true meaning of God's word, and put upon it a forced 
    construction; whereas, if we unite them, we shall almost always find its 
    just import.</p>
    <p align="justify">It is undeniable that the, verses which precede and 
    follow our text refer to sanctification, see, verse 1-14; nor is there 
    anything which properly relates to our justification: and therefore we have 
    a strong presumptive ground for interpreting the words of our text in 
    reference to the new nature, which is spoken of in the verse immediately 
    before it: nor could anything but the peculiarity of the expression lead one 
    for a moment to look for any other sense. </p>
    <p align="justify">But it seems that to interpret the word "Christ," as 
    meaning the image of Christ, or the New Man, is to take a great, and almost 
    an unwarrantable liberty with Scripture. Nevertheless, if we compare some 
    other passages with the text, see <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/2%20Cor%2013.5" data-reference="2 Cor 13.5" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2 Corinthians 13:5</a>, where "Christ in us" 
    must be understood of his image, because it is that whereby we are to 
    ascertain whether we are in the faith. See also <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Gal%204.19" data-reference="Gal 4.19" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Galatians 4:19</a>, where 
    "Christ formed in us" cannot be understood of Christ personally, but of 
    Christ spiritually, that is of his image. Above all, see <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Rom%2013.14" data-reference="Rom 13.14" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Romans 13:14</a>, where 
    the very metaphor which occurs in our context, is used. "Put on the new 
    man," says our context, "for Christ," that is, the putting on of Christ, or 
    of the new man, "is all." And, in the passage referred to, is the very 
    expression, "Put on the Lord Jesus Christ", we shall find that we are fully 
    authorized to put this construction upon it, and that there is no necessity 
    to understand it in any other way than that which the context so evidently 
    requires.</p>
    <p align="justify">The meaning then of the words before us is simply this: 
    we should be daily putting off our old and corrupt nature, and be putting on 
    a new and holy nature; because nothing else will be at all regarded by God. 
    Whatever advantages we possess, we have nothing, if we are not holy. On the 
    other hand, whatever disadvantages we labor under, we shall suffer no loss, 
    if we are holy: for the image of "Christ" on the soul "is all, in all" 
    persons, and under all circumstances. Where that is, God will be pleased; 
    and where that is not, he will be eternally displeased.</p>
    <p align="justify">In order to confirm this momentous truth, we shall show, 
    that, in the eyes of God, our restoration to the Divine image "is all in 
    all." It is,</p>
    <b><font color="#0000ff">
    <p align="justify">I. The one scope of all God's plans—</p>
    </font>
    <p align="justify">God's design in the redemption of the world at large—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">When first he determined to rescue man from perdition, he 
    decreed that he would "create us anew in Christ Jesus unto good works, in 
    which he ordained that we should walk, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Eph%202.10" data-reference="Eph 2.10" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ephesians 2:10</a>.</p>
    <p align="justify">The means which he used for the accomplishment of our 
    salvation had especial respect to this end, not to save us <i>in </i>our 
    sins, but <i>from </i>them, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Matt%201.21" data-reference="Matt 1.21" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Matthew 1:21</a>. <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Acts%203.26" data-reference="Acts 3.26" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Acts 3:26</a>.</p>
    <p align="justify">He sent his only dear Son to take our nature, and in that 
    nature to live, to die, to rise again. But in all this he aimed, not at our
    <i>happiness </i>merely, but our restoration to the <i>holy image </i>which 
    we had lost, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Gal%201.4" data-reference="Gal 1.4" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Galatians 1:4</a>. <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Pet%201.18-19" data-reference="1 Pet 1.18-19" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Peter 1:18-19</a>; <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Pet%202.24" data-reference="1 Pet 2.24" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Peter 2:24</a>. <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Titus%202.14" data-reference="Titus 2.14" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Titus 2:14</a>." This 
    is specified in terms peculiarly strong and energetic, in order that we may 
    not overlook this truth as if it were only of secondary importance, 
    <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Eph%205.25-27" data-reference="Eph 5.25-27" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ephesians 5:25-27</a>.</p>
    <p align="justify">He gave his Holy Spirit also for the same end, he gave 
    him:<br>
    to humble us, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/John%2016.8-11" data-reference="John 16.8-11" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">John 16:8-11</a>, <br>
    to renew us, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Titus%203.5-6" data-reference="Titus 3.5-6" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Titus 3:5-6</a>, <br>
    to mortify all our vile lusts and passions, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Rom%208.13" data-reference="Rom 8.13" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Romans 8:13</a>, <br>
    to fashion us after the Divine image, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Eph%204.23-24" data-reference="Eph 4.23-24" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ephesians 4:23-24</a> with <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/2%20Cor%201.22" data-reference="2 Cor 1.22" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2 Corinthians 
    1:22</a>. </p>
    <p align="justify">A "seal" is an impress of the Divine image; and a 
    "pledge" is the commencement of heavenly purity and joy, and to perfect that 
    image in our souls, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/2%20Cor%203.18" data-reference="2 Cor 3.18" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2 Corinthians 3:18</a>.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">God's design in imparting that redemption to individuals—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">Why did he choose any of us from before the foundation of 
    the world? It was "that we might be holy, and without blame before him in 
    love, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Eph%201.4" data-reference="Eph 1.4" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ephesians 1:4</a>." </p>
    <p align="justify">Why has he revealed his grace in our hearts? It was to 
    "teach us, that, denying ungodliness and worldly lusts, we should live 
    righteously, soberly, and godly in this present world, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Titus%202.11-12" data-reference="Titus 2.11-12" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Titus 2:11-12</a>." </p>
    <p align="justify">If he applies his promises to our souls, or hides his 
    face from us, it is alike "for our profit, that we may be partakers of his 
    holiness <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/2%20Cor%207.1" data-reference="2 Cor 7.1" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2 Corinthians 7:1</a> with <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Heb%2012.10" data-reference="Heb 12.10" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hebrews 12:10</a>." </p>
    <p align="justify">Whatever be his dispensations towards us, "this is his 
    will, even our sanctification, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Thess%204.3" data-reference="1 Thess 4.3" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Thessalonians 4:3</a>;" and this is his 
    ultimate design in all, even:<br>
    to "carry on the good work he has begun, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Phil%201.6" data-reference="Phil 1.6" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Philippians 1:6</a>," <br>
    to "sanctify us wholly <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Thess%205.23" data-reference="1 Thess 5.23" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Thessalonians 5:23</a>," and <br>
    to "perfect that which concerns us <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Ps%20138.8" data-reference="Ps 138.8" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Psalm 138:8</a>."</p>
    <p align="justify">But holiness is also,</p>
    <b><font color="#0000ff">
    <p align="justify">II. The one object of God's regard—</p>
    </font>
    <p align="justify">Nothing but holiness is regarded by him in this world—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">The external ordinances of religion are not only 
    worthless, but even, hateful, in his sight, if destitute of solid piety, 
    <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Isa%201.11-16" data-reference="Isa 1.11-16" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Isaiah 1:11-16</a>. On the other hand, the smallest particle of genuine holiness 
    is not overlooked by him, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Kings%2014.13" data-reference="1 Kings 14.13" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Kings 14:13</a>. Even the semblance of it has 
    sometimes been rewarded by him, in order that he might show to mankind how 
    great a value he has for it, where it really exists, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Kings%2021.29" data-reference="1 Kings 21.29" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Kings 21:29</a>. One 
    single disposition is declared by him to be of great price in his sight, 1 
    Peter 3:4. The purposes which have never been realized in act, are highly 
    commended by him, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Kings%208.18" data-reference="1 Kings 8.18" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Kings 8:18</a>. And wherever he sees a person laboring to do 
    his will, he invariably reveals to him his love in a more abundant measure, 
    <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/John%2014.23" data-reference="John 14.23" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">John 14:23</a>, and communicates to him his richest blessings, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Isa%2058.10-11" data-reference="Isa 58.10-11" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Isaiah 58:10-11</a>.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">Nothing but holiness will be regarded by him in the world 
    to come—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">When we shall stand at the judgment-seat of Christ, the 
    inquiry will be, not, what we have <i>professed</i>, but what we have <i>
    done</i>, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Matt%207.21-23" data-reference="Matt 7.21-23" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Matthew 7:21-23</a>; <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Matt%2025.31-46" data-reference="Matt 25.31-46" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Matthew 25:31-46</a>; and a Gentile who has served 
    God according to the light that he enjoyed, will be preferred before the 
    Christian professor, who has not made a suitable improvement of his superior 
    advantages, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Rom%202.25-27" data-reference="Rom 2.25-27" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Romans 2:25-27</a>. Apparently trivial occurrences will be noticed 
    in that day; and rewards will be dispensed, not according to the greatness 
    and splendor of our actions, but according to their intrinsic qualities, and 
    to the principle evinced by them, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Matt%2010.42" data-reference="Matt 10.42" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Matthew 10:42</a>. </p>
    <p align="justify">We must not indeed imagine that there is any merit in our 
    poor services, for there is imperfection in them all; and, "if we had done 
    all that is commanded us, still we would be only unprofitable servants:" but 
    God delights in holiness; and wherever he beholds it, he will, of his own 
    grace and mercy, bestow upon it a proportionate reward, exalting those to 
    the highest thrones in glory, who have made the greatest improvement of the 
    talents committed to them, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Matt%2025.19-23" data-reference="Matt 25.19-23" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Matthew 25:19-23</a>.</p>
    <p align="justify">There will be no distinction made, except what is 
    grounded on the different degrees of conformity to the Divine image which 
    the different individuals have attained. God will not respect the 
    circumcised more than the uncircumcised, or the rich and learned more than 
    the poor and illiterate. <i>In all persons equally, the image of Christ will 
    be sought for; and the possession, or lack of it, will determine their 
    eternal state</i>. "Christ will then be, as he now is, all, and in all!"</p>
    <b><font color="#0000ff">
    <p align="justify">We conclude with inquiring: Who among you is like-minded 
    with God?</p>
    </font>
    <p align="justify">1. You worldly people—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">How far are you from according with God. With him, Christ 
    is all; with you, the world. If you may but enjoy the pleasures, the honors, 
    the riches of the world, you care not about the image of Christ: to be rich 
    in faith and good works is not the object of your ambition—that you leave to 
    the old, the sick, the enthusiasts. </p>
    <p align="justify">But ah! if Christ is all, as indeed he is, think what a 
    vanity you are pursuing: think how poor you will be in the day of judgment; 
    and how you will then execrate your present ways. Be persuaded to be wise in 
    time: and beg without delay that "Christ may be made unto you wisdom, and 
    righteousness, and sanctification, and redemption, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Cor%201.30" data-reference="1 Cor 1.30" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Corinthians 1:30</a>."</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">2. You self-deceiving religious professors—</p>
    </b><i>
    </i><p align="justify"><i>How many are there in the Church, who will talk about 
    Christ, and speak of him as the ground of all their hopes, while yet they 
    are shamefully destitute of his image! </i>Yes, grievous it is to say, that 
    there are "many vain-talkers and deceivers" now, as well as in the apostolic 
    age: <br>
    many who are proud and passionate; <br>
    many who are earthly-minded and covetous; <br>
    many who are unchaste and lewd; <br>
    many that are deceitful in their words, and dishonest in their dealings; <br>
    many, in short, whose tempers, and dispositions, and conduct, are a disgrace 
    to their profession. </p>
    <p align="justify">If such there are here present, know that <i>you are as 
    unlike to God as Satan himself is! </i>Know that all your knowledge, all 
    your experiences, and all your professions, will only aggravate your 
    condemnation, if you die in your present state! <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Job%2036.13" data-reference="Job 36.13" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Job 36:13</a>. </p>
    <p align="justify">You do well to rely on Christ, and to make him your all 
    in point of dependence; but know for a certainty, that, however you may 
    pretend to trust in him, you never can he saved by him, unless you become 
    new creatures! <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/2%20Cor%205.17" data-reference="2 Cor 5.17" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2 Corinthians 5:17</a>; for "without holiness no man shall see 
    the Lord <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Heb%2012.14" data-reference="Heb 12.14" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hebrews 12:14</a>."</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">3. You true believers—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">You can appeal to God that you are like-minded with him 
    in this grand point; and that <i>you desire as much to be saved from sin, as 
    to be delivered from Hell itself</i>. This is a blessed evidence that you 
    are born of God, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20John%203.10" data-reference="1 John 3.10" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 John 3:10</a>. While you are thus panting after holiness, you 
    have nothing to fear—your faith is sound, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/James%202.22" data-reference="James 2.22" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">James 2:22</a>. your hope is 
    scriptural, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20John%203.3" data-reference="1 John 3.3" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 John 3:3</a>, and saving, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Rom%205.5" data-reference="Rom 5.5" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Romans 5:5</a>; <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Rom%208.24" data-reference="Rom 8.24" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Romans 8:24</a>. Go on then from 
    grace to grace, from strength to strength, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/2%20Pet%203.18" data-reference="2 Pet 3.18" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2 Peter 3:18</a>. Be daily putting 
    off the old man with its lusts, verse 8, 9, and putting on the new man with 
    all its characteristic graces, verse 12, 13. Be "growing up thus into Christ 
    in all things as your living Head, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Eph%204.15" data-reference="Eph 4.15" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ephesians 4:15</a>." until you have arrived 
    at the full measure of the stature of Christ! <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Eph%204.13" data-reference="Eph 4.13" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ephesians 4:13</a>; and when you 
    have attained a perfect fitness for the enjoyment of your God, you shall be
    <i>like </i>him, and <i>with </i>him for ever! <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20John%203.2" data-reference="1 John 3.2" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 John 3:2</a>.</p>
    <p align="justify">&nbsp;</p>
    <font color="#ff0000"><b>
    <p align="justify">#2186</p>
    <p align="justify">CHRISTIAN CHARACTER DISPLAYED</p>
    <p align="justify"><a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Col%203.12-15" data-reference="Col 3.12-15" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Colossians 3:12-15</a> </p>
    </b></font>
    <p align="justify">"Therefore, as God's chosen people, holy and dearly 
    loved, clothe yourselves with compassion, kindness, humility, gentleness and 
    patience. Bear with each other and forgive whatever grievances you may have 
    against one another. Forgive as the Lord forgave you. And over all these 
    virtues put on love, which binds them all together in perfect unity. Let the 
    peace of Christ rule in your hearts, since as members of one body you were 
    called to peace. And be thankful."</p>
    <p align="justify">THE end of Christianity is to restore man to the Divine 
    image, in order to his ultimate restoration to the blessedness which he has 
    forfeited and lost. Nor does God ever accomplish the latter but through the 
    medium of the former. </p>
    <p align="justify">Doubtless the Lord Jesus Christ, by his own obedience 
    unto death, effects our reconciliation with God: that is his work, and his 
    alone. </p>
    <p align="justify">But our "fitness for the inheritance of the saints in 
    light" is the work of his Holy Spirit, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Col%201.12" data-reference="Col 1.12" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Colossians 1:12</a>; and it is wrought in 
    every one of "God's elect:" for no one is "chosen to salvation but through 
    the sanctification of the Spirit, united with, and added to, the sprinkling 
    of the blood of Jesus Christ, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Pet%201.2" data-reference="1 Pet 1.2" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Peter 1:2</a>."</p>
    <p align="justify">Hence, in the chapter before us, the Apostle marks 
    distinctly wherein that renovation consists: it is "a putting off of the old 
    man, and a putting on of the new man, which, after God, is created in 
    righteousness and true holiness, verse 9, 10 with <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Eph%204.24" data-reference="Eph 4.24" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ephesians 4:24</a>." </p>
    <p align="justify">The particular <i>evils of the old man</i>, which are to 
    be put off, are enumerated in, verse 8, 9. The <i>particular graces of the 
    new man</i>, which are to be put on, are stated in the words of my text: 
    and, inasmuch as this transformation of the soul into the Divine image, or 
    "the forming of Christ within us," is that which, beyond all other marks of 
    distinction, will operate to our final acceptance with God. This is the 
    meaning of "Christ is all," that is the image of Christ. Compare <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Gal%204.19" data-reference="Gal 4.19" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Galatians 
    4:19</a>.</p>
    <p align="justify">The Apostle urges us to meet God, as it were, upon his 
    own terms: "Put on, therefore," the new man: and he urges us, by the 
    consideration of the distinguishing grace which we ourselves have received: 
    "Put on, therefore, as the elect of God, holy and beloved," this new man. 
    Now, the attainment of this change is what we all profess to hope for; and, 
    therefore, it should be sought by us with all diligence, and be manifested 
    by us ill the whole of our life and conduct.</p>
    <p align="justify">To impress this upon your minds, I will show,</p>
    <font color="#0000ff"><b>
    <p align="justify">I. Wherein true Christian character consists—</p>
    </b></font>
    <p align="justify">If we would have a full view of this subject, we must 
    enter into the Christian's experience before God. But that would lead us 
    beyond the proper scope of our text, which confines our attention to the 
    Christian in his daily walk before man. Adhering then to our text, let us 
    see what the Christian should be:</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">1. What the Christian should be, in the daily habit of 
    his <u>mind</u>—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">You cannot but know, brethren, what proud, selfish 
    creatures we are by nature; caring for nothing but our own ease, pleasure, 
    honor, and advancement. Except in very particular cases, where relative or 
    social ties have created a more than ordinary interest in our minds, how 
    little do we feel for those around us; either for those with whom we have 
    more immediate fellowship, or those who are bowed down with sorrows of any 
    kind!</p>
    <p align="justify">But, in opposition to these hateful dispositions, we 
    should put on:<br>
    in the place of indifference, compassion; <br>
    in the place of roughness, courtesy; <br>
    and in the place of pride, humility. </p>
    <p align="justify">We may conceive how a mother's affections would yearn 
    over her first-born child, when writhing in agony, and perishing through 
    want. Such "affections of mercies should we put on" towards all who are in 
    want or trouble of any kind; participating, at least by sympathy, in the 
    sorrows which we cannot alleviate in any other way. And towards every person 
    with whom we come in contact, whether he be a superior, an equal, or an 
    inferior; yes, and whether he be a friend or foe—we should "put on 
    kindness," and exercise nothing but benevolence. As least of all, we would 
    be ever ready to take the lowest place, "putting on humbleness of mind," 
    and, with unaffected simplicity, rendering ourselves the servants of all 
    around us. This, I say, should be the daily habit of our minds; not called 
    forth by great exertion, but operating readily, naturally, habitually, as 
    the feelings of a mother towards her infant offspring.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">2. What the Christian should be, in his <u>deportment 
    towards others</u>—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">Here, alas! we cannot but be sensible:<br>
    what <i>irritability </i>we have shown on the slightest occasions; <br>
    what <i>displeasure</i>, when an offense has been of any continuance; <br>
    what <i>alienation </i>we have felt from those who differ from us in their 
    opinions and conduct;<br>
    what <i>vindictiveness</i>, when any serious injury has been sustained by 
    us. </p>
    <p align="justify">But all of this is sadly unfitting to us as the followers 
    of Christ, whom, by every possible consideration, we are bound to imitate 
    and resemble. For anger, we should "put on meekness;" and "long-suffering," 
    in the place of retaliation or complaint. Instead of harboring intolerance, 
    we should "put on forbearance;" and, instead of retaining a vindictive 
    spirit against any, we should call to mind how many and great offenses 
    Christ has forgiven us; and would gladly "mete to our fellow-creatures the 
    measure which we ourselves have received from him." This is the spirit which 
    we are to manifest on all occasions; and this is to be the constant tenor of 
    our way in all our fellowship with mankind.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">3. What the Christian should be, in the <u>governing 
    principle of his life</u>—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">Here is man's great defect. By nature we are altogether 
    enrapt up in <u>self</u>. <i>Self </i>is the principle that actuates us in 
    everything, and the end for which alone we live. Self-seeking, 
    self-pleasing, self-interest, occupy, for the most part, our every thought, 
    and regulate our every motion. But there is a new principle that is imparted 
    to the Christian, and under its influence his whole life must be directed: 
    and this is the principle of love. This is the root and essence of every 
    other grace: it comprehends all, combines all, consolidates all. Whatever 
    there be that enters into the composition of Christian "perfection, this is 
    the bond" which unites it altogether, and forms it into one harmonious mass.
    </p>
    <p align="justify">It is the spirit which pervades and actuates every 
    faculty of the soul, even as the soul directs and regulates every member of 
    the body. The soul, in operation, causes every member to perform its proper 
    office; and love, presiding, will keep every Christian grace in full 
    activity. This, therefore, we must "put on, over all, and above all" the 
    other graces that have been mentioned; so that nothing may be lacking to the 
    proper discharge of all our duties.</p>
    <p align="justify">That I may the better commend to you this state of mind, 
    I will endeavor to point out,</p>
    <font color="#0000ff"><b>
    <p align="justify">II. The vast importance of Christian love—</p>
    </b></font>
    <p align="justify">Notice particularly what the Apostle urges in my text: 
    "Put on, as the elect of God, holy and beloved," these several graces. </p>
    <p align="justify">God calls for it;<br>
    man expects it; <br>
    consistency requires it.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">1. God calls for it—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">You are his elect. But to what has he called you? Not to 
    salvation only, but "unto holiness, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Thess%204.7" data-reference="1 Thess 4.7" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Thessalonians 4:7</a>." Hear particularly 
    how Paul states this matter: "God has chosen us in Christ before the 
    foundation of the world, that we should be holy and without blame before him 
    in love, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Eph%201.4" data-reference="Eph 1.4" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ephesians 1:4</a>." And again: "He has predestined us to be conformed 
    to the image of his Son, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Rom%208.29" data-reference="Rom 8.29" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Romans 8:29</a>." </p>
    <p align="justify">Now if, instead of cultivating these graces, we retain 
    "the old man" in all its power and efficiency, we defeat the very object 
    which God, supposing him to have elected us, has had in view. And will God 
    endure that? Our blessed Lord said, "Have not I chosen you twelve; and one 
    of you is a devil? <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/John%206.70" data-reference="John 6.70" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">John 6:70</a>." Know, then, if we continue devils, as Judas 
    did, we shall, with him, "go to our own place! <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Acts%201.25" data-reference="Acts 1.25" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Acts 1:25</a>," and not to the 
    habitation of the just. We can never be "beloved" of our God, if we are not 
    "holy."</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">2. Man expects it—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">If we profess to be "the elect of God," man will very 
    reasonably demand a proof of it. We may tell him of our faith: but he will 
    reply, "Show me your works. As for your faith, God alone can judge of that: 
    but I must judge of the tree by its fruits: and, it you profess to be 
    distinguished above your fellows by the special favor of your God, I have a 
    right to ask: What do you more than others <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Matt%205.47" data-reference="Matt 5.47" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Matthew 5:47</a>." Have you "put off 
    the old man, which is corrupt according to the deceitful lusts; and put on 
    the new man, which, after God, is created in righteousness and true 
    holiness? <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Eph%204.22-24" data-reference="Eph 4.22-24" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ephesians 4:22-24</a>." Let me see what your tempers are in your 
    family, and towards all around you, and especially under circumstances of 
    heavy trial. Tell me not of your inward experiences before God. I must judge 
    by your spirit and conduct towards man: and, if I find you not endued with 
    the graces of the Spirit, I can account you no better than others; yes, 
    rather, I must account you worse; since, with all your high professions, you 
    are no better than hypocrites and deceivers!"</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">3. Consistency requires it—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">This is the peculiar force of my text. When we call 
    ourselves "the elect of God," we profess to have been "renewed in the spirit 
    of our mind;" for, if we do not profess this, the most abandoned reprobate 
    in the universe has as much right to call himself "elect," as we. </p>
    <p align="justify">"Are you, then, destitute of compassion? How dwells the 
    love of God in you? <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20John%203.17" data-reference="1 John 3.17" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 John 3:17</a>."</p>
    <p align="justify">Are you proud, passionate, intolerant, unforgiving? "Lie 
    not against the truth <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/James%203.14" data-reference="James 3.14" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">James 3:14</a>;" you are "children of darkness, and not of 
    light;" "not children of God, but children of the devil, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20John%203.7-10" data-reference="1 John 3.7-10" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 John 3:7-10</a>." <i>
    To "call Christ, Lord, Lord," without walking in his steps, is only to 
    deceive and ruin your own souls!</i></p><i>
    </i><b><font color="#0000ff">
    <p align="justify">Behold then, brethren,</p>
    </font>
    <p align="justify">1. The excellence of Christian principles—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">Christianity requires us to refer all good to God; and to 
    say, after all that we have attained, "By the grace of God, I am what I am! 
    <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Cor%2015.10" data-reference="1 Cor 15.10" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Corinthians 15:10</a>." But will this tend to encourage us in sin? No, "the 
    grace of God, which brings salvation, teaches us, that, denying ungodliness 
    and worldly lusts, we should live soberly, righteously, and godly, in this 
    present world! <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Titus%202.11-12" data-reference="Titus 2.11-12" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Titus 2:11-12</a>;" and "the hope that we have in Christ will, of 
    necessity, lead us to purify ourselves, even as He is pure! <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20John%203.3" data-reference="1 John 3.3" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 John 3:3</a>."</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">2. The beauty of the Christian character—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">Look at a man clothed, as my text describes, in all those 
    lovely graces; and "so clothed with them," as never to be seen without them: 
    and then tell me, whether he is not a lovely character. </p>
    <p align="justify">Is there a man in the universe that does not admire 
    "affections of mercies, kindness, humbleness of mind, meekness, 
    long-suffering, forbearance, and forgiveness," and all under the direction 
    and government of "love?" I grant, that, from envy and jealousy, the world 
    may be filled with rage against a person possessing all these graces: for so 
    were they incensed against our blessed Lord himself, in whom these virtues 
    existed in their utmost possible perfection; but this was on other grounds 
    than on account of his virtues. He professed himself the Messiah; and 
    therefore they put him to death: his tempers, and dispositions, and habits, 
    they could not but admire. And so, at this day, the men that hate us, under 
    the idea of "God's elect," cannot but acknowledge that the consistent 
    Christian is, of all characters, the loveliest upon the face of the earth! 1 
    Peter 3:4. I call upon all of you therefore, brethren, to "show forth these 
    virtues;" and thus to "put to silence the ignorance of foolish men, by 
    well-doing! <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Pet%202.15" data-reference="1 Pet 2.15" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Peter 2:15</a>."</p>
    <p align="justify">&nbsp;</p>
    <p align="justify"></p>
    <font color="#ff0000"><b>
    <p align="justify">#2187</p>
    <p align="justify">LOVE TO THE SCRIPTURES RECOMMENDED</p>
    <p align="justify"><a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Col%203.16" data-reference="Col 3.16" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Colossians 3:16</a></p>
    </b></font>
    <p align="justify">"Let the word of Christ dwell in you richly!"</p>
    <p align="justify">IT was declared to be one of the principal advantages 
    which the Jews enjoyed above the heathen, that they had "the Oracles of God 
    committed to them, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Rom%203.1-2" data-reference="Rom 3.1-2" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Romans 3:1-2</a>;" and we are still more highly privileged, 
    in that we have in our hands the New Testament Scriptures, whereby we are 
    enabled to understand the writings of Moses and the prophets more fully than 
    the writers themselves understood them. </p>
    <p align="justify">What part of the Christian records the Colossians could 
    possess, we do not exactly know: we are sure that the sacred canon was not 
    yet complete; nor were the different epistles which have come down to us, 
    collected into one volume. It is probable enough that one or two of the 
    Gospels might have been seen by them: and the possession of such a treasure 
    would be a very sufficient ground for the exhortation before us. </p>
    <p align="justify">To us who enjoy a complete collection of all that God has 
    ever seen fit to reveal—at least, as much of it as is at all necessary for 
    our edification and comfort—the exhortation may be addressed with 
    proportionably greater weight. To impress it the more powerfully upon your 
    minds, we shall take occasion from it to show you in what light the sacred 
    volume should be regarded, and in what manner it should be improved.</p>
    <font color="#0000ff"><b>
    <p align="justify">I. In what light the Scripture should be regarded—</p>
    </b></font>
    <p align="justify">The word which has been transmitted to us was written by 
    different men, in different and distant ages of the world. But though it was 
    written by men, it is indeed the Word of God; because those holy men wrote 
    under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/2%20Pet%201.21" data-reference="2 Pet 1.21" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2 Peter 1:21</a>. Indeed, the word is, 
    properly and strictly speaking, "the word of Christ"—</p>
    <p align="justify">Our blessed and adorable Lord ministered to the Church 
    not only before his incarnation, but from the very beginning of the world. 
    It was He who preached by Noah to the antediluvian world, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Pet%203.18-20" data-reference="1 Pet 3.18-20" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Peter 3:18-20</a>. 
    It was He who inspired all the prophets in all succeeding ages of the 
    Church; and enabled them to testify beforehand respecting his future 
    sufferings and glory, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Pet%201.10-11" data-reference="1 Pet 1.10-11" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Peter 1:10-11</a>. Thus was he the real Author of the 
    Old Testament. </p>
    <p align="justify">With respect to the New Testament, whatever is revealed 
    there must also be traced to the same source. It was Christ who taught his 
    Apostles, and who "by his Spirit brought all things to their remembrance," 
    and, in a personal appearance to Saul, revealed to him the whole scheme and 
    plan of redemption, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Gal%201.11-12" data-reference="Gal 1.11-12" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Galatians 1:11-12</a>. What the Apostles spoke in his name, 
    they affirmed to be, not the word of man, but of God, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Thess%202.13" data-reference="1 Thess 2.13" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Thessalonians 2:13</a>; 
    and what they wrote in their epistles, they declared to be "the commandment 
    of their Lord, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Cor%2014.37" data-reference="1 Cor 14.37" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Corinthians 14:37</a>." Hence every part of the sacred volume 
    is justly called by the Apostle "the word of Christ."</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">In this view it ought to be regarded by us—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">Let us suppose that the Lord Jesus Christ were now to 
    come among us, and to teach in our Churches, as once he did in the streets 
    and synagogues of Judea: would we not, if we knew him to be that very Jesus, 
    listen to him with the deepest attention? Would we not revolve in our 
    thoughts the various subjects of his discourse, and labor to ascertain their 
    true import? If we could suppose him now addressing us from the cross, and 
    appealing to his sufferings as an unquestionable demonstration of his love, 
    and an irresistible argument for our adherence to him; would we not be 
    melted to tears? Would we not be ready to exclaim, "What have we to do any 
    more with idols?" "Other lords have had dominion over us; but by you only 
    will we make mention of your name." </p>
    <p align="justify">Or, lastly, let us suppose that we saw the heavens 
    opened, and Jesus standing at the right hand of God, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Acts%207.56" data-reference="Acts 7.56" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Acts 7:56</a>; let us 
    suppose he spoke to us now, as once he did from Mount Sinai, with 
    thunderings, and lightnings, and earthquakes, and the sound of the trumpet 
    waxing louder and louder, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Heb%2012.18-19" data-reference="Heb 12.18-19" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hebrews 12:18-19</a>; would we not tremble? Would we 
    not be ready to engage, as the Israelites did, "All that the Lord has spoken 
    will we do, and be obedient?" </p>
    <p align="justify">Were we to hear him speaking to us in any of these ways, 
    the word would not more certainly be his, than this word is which we now 
    possess: and therefore whatever opinions of fear or love or gratitude we 
    would feel on account of such revelations of his will, we ought to feel in 
    reference to that sacred volume which we have in our hands. Whenever we look 
    upon it, we should say, This is the word: <br>
    of Him who came down from Heaven to instruct me; <br>
    of Him who died upon the cross to save me; <br>
    of Him who now sits enthroned in glory, and will hereafter fix my eternal 
    doom according to it! <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/John%2012.48" data-reference="John 12.48" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">John 12:48</a>.</p>
    <p align="justify">Let us next inquire,</p>
    <font color="#0000ff"><b>
    <p align="justify">II. In what manner the Scripture should be improved—</p>
    </b></font>
    <p align="justify">We should not merely regard it with pious veneration, 
    but, should make use of it,</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">1. For the furnishing of our <u>minds</u>—</p>
    </b><i>
    </i><p align="justify"><i>It is to little purpose to have the Scriptures in our 
    homes, unless we read them diligently, and acquire an experimental and 
    practical knowledge of them. </i>As the tables of the law were deposited 
    within the ark, so should the whole "Word of God be hidden within our 
    hearts." It should "dwell in us;" it should dwell in us "richly;" its <i>
    precepts </i>should be treasured up in our minds, that we may know what the 
    will of the Lord is: its <i>promises </i>should be precious to us, that we 
    may be able to plead them at the throne of grace, and obtain the 
    accomplishment of them to our own souls: nor would its <i>threatenings </i>
    be overlooked, but rather be considered as kind and beneficial admonitions 
    which are given us for our good.</p>
    <p align="justify">It will be said by many, that their memory is defective, 
    and that they cannot retain the things which they read or hear: but if we 
    made a practice of selecting daily some short portion of Scripture for our 
    meditation throughout the day, the most ignorant among us would soon attain 
    a knowledge which at present appears far beyond his reach.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">2. For the regulating of our <u>conduct</u>—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">Speculative knowledge, for the most part, tends only to 
    pride and contention. That which alone is valuable to the Christian, is 
    practical. The Scriptures are designed to lead him to such wisdom and 
    discretion as will be in vain sought for from any other source. Indeed "all 
    wisdom" is to be "drawn from these wells of salvation." </p>
    <p align="justify">The person whose mind is cast into the mold of the 
    Scripture, will view everything as God views it: he will have the same 
    practical judgment as God himself has. "Good and evil, light and darkness" 
    will not be confounded in his mind, as they are in the minds of ungodly men: 
    he will distinguish them with ease, except in cases that are very obscure 
    and complicated. By means of the spiritual discernment which he has 
    obtained, he will be able to judge of the conduct of others, while they are 
    not able to appreciate him, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Cor%202.14-15" data-reference="1 Cor 2.14-15" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Corinthians 2:14-15</a>; and as far as his actions 
    are regulated by his principles, he will be a light to all around him; and 
    they shall be constrained to "acknowledge that God is with them in truth,"
    </p>
    <p align="justify">Indeed it is for this end that God sets up a light in his 
    people's souls, "not that it may be put under a bushel, but that it may be 
    set on a candlestick, and give light to all that are in the house;" and that 
    the person possessing it may be able to say to all around him, "Whatever you 
    have <i>seen </i>and <i>heard </i>in me, do; and the God of peace shall be 
    with you."</p>
    <b><font color="#0000ff">
    <p align="justify">That we may enforce the exhortation in our text, we would 
    remind you, that a love to the Scriptures is,</p>
    </font>
    <p align="justify">1. An inseparable attendant on true piety—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">Look at the most distinguished saints, and see how they 
    regarded the inspired records. <i>Job </i>esteemed the words of God's mouth 
    more than his necessary food, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Job%2023.12" data-reference="Job 23.12" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Job 23:12</a>. <i>Jeremiah </i>found them the "joy 
    and rejoicing of his heart, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Jer%2015.16" data-reference="Jer 15.16" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Jeremiah 15:16</a>." And to David they were "sweeter 
    than honey and the honey-comb, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Ps%2019.10" data-reference="Ps 19.10" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Psalm 19:10</a>." Let not us then think that we 
    have any title to be classed with those holy men, if we do not resemble them 
    in this particular.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">2. A necessary means of advancement in every part of the 
    divine life—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">Have we been only just quickened from the dead? We cannot 
    but love that which has been the means of giving us life, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Ps%20119.93" data-reference="Ps 119.93" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Psalm 119:93</a>. </p>
    <p align="justify">Are we as new-born babes? we must of necessity "desire 
    the sincere milk of the word, that we may grow thereby, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Pet%202.2" data-reference="1 Pet 2.2" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Peter 2:2</a>." </p>
    <p align="justify">Have we arrived at the strength and stature of youth? 
    "that word must abide within us, in order that we may be able to overcome" 
    the great adversary of our souls, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20John%202.14" data-reference="1 John 2.14" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 John 2:14</a>. </p>
    <p align="justify">In a word, whatever state we be in, it is "by the 
    Scriptures that we are to be furnished for every good word and work, 2 
    Timothy 3:16-17."</p>
    <p align="justify">&nbsp;</p>
    <font color="#ff0000"><b>
    <p align="justify">#2188</p>
    <p align="justify">DOING ALL IN THE NAME OF CHRIST</p>
    <p align="justify"><a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Col%203.17" data-reference="Col 3.17" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Colossians 3:17</a></p>
    </b></font>
    <p align="justify">"Whatever you do in word or deed, do all in the name of 
    the Lord Jesus, giving thanks to God and the Father by him."</p>
    <p align="justify">SUPPOSING the existence of one Supreme Being to be 
    acknowledged, our obvious duty towards him must be to exercise such a 
    dependence on him, as shall evince a consciousness, that "in him we live, 
    and move, and have our being, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Acts%2017.28" data-reference="Acts 17.28" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Acts 17:28</a>." This being what, for 
    distinction's sake, I will call <i>natural religion</i>, we may see what 
    must, of necessity, be required of us under the Christian dispensation. </p>
    <p align="justify">By the Gospel we are informed, that the Lord Jesus Christ 
    is the Creator and Governor of the universe; and, consequently, must be 
    entitled to all that regard which, as Theists, we pay to the Supreme Being. 
    But He is further revealed to us as the Redeemer of the world; and, 
    consequently, as standing in a still nearer relation to us, as our vital 
    Head; from whom we derive all supplies of grace and peace, and to whom we 
    must ascribe all the blessings which we enjoy, whether in time or in 
    eternity.</p>
    <p align="justify">What, then, is evangelical religion? It is not<i> a mere 
    assent to certain principles</i>, however accurate those principles may be. 
    Nor is it <i>a practice of certain duties</i>, however commendable those 
    duties may be. It is a habit of mind, by means of which Christ's universal 
    agency is acknowledged, and the whole soul goes forth to him; receiving 
    everything from his fullness, and improving everything for his glory.</p>
    <p align="justify">To unfold this more clearly, I will endeavor to show, 
    what, under the Gospel dispensation, should be the habit of our minds,</p>
    <font color="#0000ff"><b>
    <p align="justify">I. In all that we do for God—</p>
    </b></font>
    <p align="justify">In my text, we are told to do everything "in the name of 
    Jesus Christ." Now, by this expression, I understand that we should do 
    everything,</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">1. From respect to his authority—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">Paul says, "We command you, in the name of our Lord Jesus 
    Christ, that you withdraw yourselves from every brother that walks 
    disorderly, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/2%20Thess%203.6" data-reference="2 Thess 3.6" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2 Thessalonians 3:6</a>." It was by the authority of Christ that he 
    issued that command; and from a respect to that authority was that command 
    to be obeyed. </p>
    <p align="justify">In like manner must we have respect to Christ in 
    everything that we do: for he has said, "Then are you my friends, if you do 
    whatever I command you." It must be a matter of indifference to us what man 
    may enjoin, unless it have the sanction of our blessed Lord's authority 
    also. </p>
    <p align="justify">We must always ask ourselves,<i> What does the Lord Jesus 
    Christ require of me? </i>That I will do, at all events, and under all 
    circumstances. If it is approved of man, I will do it, not so much to please 
    man, as to please the Lord: and If it is disapproved by man, I shall still 
    do it, because it will please my Lord. Nor will I be diverted from the path 
    of duty, though the whole world would combine to oppose my progress. My 
    Lord's will being clearly ascertained, I shall need nothing to encourage my 
    exertions, nor will I suffer anything to obstruct them.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">2. From love to his name—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">We read of "receiving a child in Christ's name," and of 
    "giving a cup of water in his name, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Mark%209.37" data-reference="Mark 9.37" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Mark 9:37</a>; <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Mark%209.41" data-reference="Mark 9.41" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Mark 9:41</a>;" that must import 
    that we do it from love to Christ. And this should be the one spring of all 
    our actions: "The love of Christ would constrain us! <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/2%20Cor%205.14" data-reference="2 Cor 5.14" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2 Corinthians 5:14</a>." It 
    is not necessary that there would be in our minds, on all occasions, a long 
    train of argumentation to call forth this principle: a mother needs not such 
    a process to call forth her love to her infant offspring: if an occasion 
    calls for the exercise of that principle, it is ready for action at all 
    times, and at a moment's notice. And so should it be with us, towards our 
    Lord Jesus Christ. There should be in us such a deep and abiding sense of 
    our obligations to him, that, in everything we say, and in everything we do, 
    we would desire to please him.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">3. In dependence on his grace—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">The Prophet Micah says, "All people will walk in the name 
    of his God; and we will walk in the name of the Lord our God for ever and 
    ever;" that is, in <u>an entire dependence upon him</u>. Now, to whom must 
    we look for direction in all our ways, but to the Lord Jesus Christ, who has 
    engaged, as our Shepherd, to go before us, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/John%2010.4" data-reference="John 10.4" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">John 10:4</a>, and who has told us in 
    all things to follow his steps, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Pet%202.21" data-reference="1 Pet 2.21" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Peter 2:21</a>." </p>
    <p align="justify">And on whom shall we rely for assistance in our 
    difficulties, but on him who has directed us to be "strong in the Lord, 
    <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Eph%206.10" data-reference="Eph 6.10" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ephesians 6:10</a>," and assured us that "through his strength we shall do all 
    things, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/2%20Cor%2012.9" data-reference="2 Cor 12.9" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2 Corinthians 12:9</a>. <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Phil%204.13" data-reference="Phil 4.13" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Philippians 4:13</a>." </p>
    <p align="justify">And through whom can we hope for acceptance, but through 
    Him, our Mediator and all-prevailing Intercessor, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Eph%203.18" data-reference="Eph 3.18" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ephesians 3:18</a>. <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20John%202.1-2" data-reference="1 John 2.1-2" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 John 
    2:1-2</a>.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">4. For the advancement of his glory—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">When Peter and John had healed a man that had been lame 
    from his mother's womb, the spectators were ready to ascribe the miracle 
    either to "the power or holiness of those" who had wrought it. But the 
    Apostles instantly gave the glory to the Lord Jesus Christ, in whose name, 
    and by whose power alone, it had been wrought: "Through faith in his name, 
    has made this man strong, whom you see and know. Yes, the faith which is by 
    him has given him this perfect soundness in the presence of you all, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Acts%203.6" data-reference="Acts 3.6" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Acts 
    3:6</a>; <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Acts%203.16" data-reference="Acts 3.16" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Acts 3:16</a>." </p>
    <p align="justify">Thus, whatever it is that we either say or do, we must 
    consult his glory, and labor to advance it. Nothing is too insignificant for 
    us to attend to in this view: "Whether we <i>eat </i>or <i>drink</i>, or 
    whatever we do, we must do all to the glory of God, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Cor%2010.31" data-reference="1 Cor 10.31" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Corinthians 10:31</a>." If 
    it is thought that it would be presumption to suppose that anything we can 
    do can by any means advance his glory, we quite mistake: for, in his last 
    intercessory prayer, he said, "All mine are yours, and yours are mine, and I 
    am glorified in them, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/John%2017.10" data-reference="John 17.10" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">John 17:10</a>."</p>
    <p align="justify">The same habit of mind must be cultivated, also,</p>
    <font color="#0000ff"><b>
    <p align="justify">II. In all that God does for us—</p>
    </b></font>
    <p align="justify">There may be many occurrences which, to flesh and blood, 
    are painful: yet, in them must we see nothing but an occasion of praise and 
    thanksgiving. Job blessed God as well for taking away his property as for 
    bestowing it, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Job%201.21" data-reference="Job 1.21" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Job 1:21</a>. And thus must we also "in everything give thanks," 
    knowing that "this is the will of God in Christ Jesus concerning us, 1 
    Thessalonians 5:8."</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">We, in all circumstances, have occasion to praise our 
    God—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">Those things which have the most painful aspect are yet 
    in reality the fruits of divine love: for "whom God loves, he chastens; and 
    scourges every son whom he receives, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Heb%2012.6" data-reference="Heb 12.6" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hebrews 12:6</a>." Indeed, the beneficial 
    tendency of our afflictions is often as clear and visible as if it were 
    pointed out to us by a voice from Heaven. For who does not see how <i>trials 
    wean us from the world, and purify us from our dross? </i>We are told, and 
    we find it true, that "tribulation works patience, and patience experience, 
    and experience hope, even a hope that makes not ashamed, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Rom%205.3-5" data-reference="Rom 5.3-5" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Romans 5:3-5</a>." But, 
    independent of this, so great are the blessings of redemption, that they 
    ought to swallow up, as it were, every other consideration; and to fill our 
    souls with unutterable joy and gratitude, even in the midst of all the 
    troubles that either men or devils can inflict upon us. </p>
    <p align="justify">In the first chapter of this epistle, the Apostle puts 
    this in a most striking point of view. He supposes the Colossians to be 
    oppressed with heavy and long-continued afflictions: and "he prays for 
    them," that they may be "strengthened with all power according to his 
    glorious might so that you may have great endurance and patience, and 
    joyfully giving thanks to the Father, who has qualified you to share in the 
    inheritance of the saints in the kingdom of light. For he has rescued us 
    from the dominion of darkness and brought us into the kingdom of the Son he 
    loves, in whom we have redemption, the forgiveness of sins. <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Col%201.11-14" data-reference="Col 1.11-14" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Colossians 
    1:11-14</a>." </p>
    <p align="justify">Must they under their trials be content with exercising 
    "patience?" No! Or "long-suffering?" No! They must be filled with 
    "joyfulness;" and be so borne up by a sense of God's mercy, and by the 
    wonders of redeeming love, as to have not a word to utter but in a way of 
    praise and thanksgiving. This then, beloved, is to be the frame of your 
    minds at all times; as it was of Paul and Silas, when in the prison and in 
    the stocks "they sang praises to God at midnight, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Acts%2016.25" data-reference="Acts 16.25" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Acts 16:25</a>."</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">In doing it, however, we must still have respect to the 
    Lord Jesus Christ for the acceptance of our very best services—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">Continually is this inculcated in the Scriptures of 
    truth. "We must give thanks always for all things unto God and the Father in 
    the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Eph%205.20" data-reference="Eph 5.20" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ephesians 5:20</a>." Praise is "a sacrifice 
    which must be offered" on him as our altar; and "be presented by him" as our 
    great High Priest, even as the animals were under the Jewish law, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Heb%2013.15" data-reference="Heb 13.15" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hebrews 
    13:15</a>. It is therefore called "the calves of our lips, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Hos%2014.2" data-reference="Hos 14.2" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hosea 14:2</a>." Nor can 
    any sacrifice, however holy, be "acceptable to God, but as offered to him 
    through Jesus Christ, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Pet%202.5" data-reference="1 Pet 2.5" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Peter 2:5</a>." This is particularly to be borne in mind 
    at all times. We must do on earth as they are doing in Heaven. Not a voice 
    is heard in Heaven which does not give glory to God and to the Lamb: nor on 
    earth should a soul be found that does not say, "Not unto us, O Lord, not 
    unto us, but unto your name be the praise."</p>
    <b><font color="#0000ff">
    <p align="justify">Let me now observe,</p>
    </font>
    <p align="justify">1. If this is true religion, how little is there of true 
    religion upon earth!</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">Where do you find men of the character above described? 
    How few are there, how very few, in whom this is found to be the prevailing 
    habit of their minds! An attention to doctrines is frequent; nor is regard 
    for moral duties uncommon: but such views of Christ, such respect to his 
    authority, such love to his name, such dependence on his grace, such zeal 
    for his glory, and such an overwhelming sense of his love as swallows up 
    every other feeling—where are these found? </p>
    <p align="justify">In how very small a measure are they possessed by the 
    very best among us! and how far are the generality from possessing them at 
    all! Yet it is by this standard that all Christian experience must be tried.
    </p>
    <p align="justify">My dear brethren, get your minds rightly instructed in 
    this matter; and then will you be able to form a right judgment, both of 
    your own state and of everything around you.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">2. If this is true religion, how happy a man is the true 
    Christian!</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">Doubtless the Christian must be conscious of innumerable 
    defects, and must find cause in himself for the deepest humiliation. But, in 
    proportion as he has attained this experience, tell me whether he is not 
    happy? Tell me whether he is not a far happier man than the possession of 
    the whole world could make him? I know that an ignorant ungodly world will 
    deride this as enthusiasm: but the passage which I before cited, in 
    reference to natural religion, is amply sufficient to show that this 
    experience is most rational, and indispensable to the Christian character.
    </p>
    <p align="justify">What are the feelings of one who, in the daily habit of 
    his mind, "lives, and moves, and has his being in God?" Precisely such are 
    the Christian's feelings towards the Lord Jesus Christ, only elevated by a 
    sense of redeeming love. </p>
    <p align="justify">"Believe then in Christ;" and "abide in him" by the 
    exercise of faith and love: and let him be "your life." Yes, "live 
    altogether by faith in Him who has loved you, and given himself for you." 
    Then will you "rejoice in him even now, with a joy that is unspeakable and 
    full of glory," and soon be partakers of "all the fullness of joy at God's 
    right hand for evermore!"</p>
    <p align="justify">&nbsp;</p>
    <font color="#ff0000"><b>
    <p align="justify">#2189</p>
    <p align="justify">THE RELATIVE DUTIES EXPLAINED</p>
    <p align="justify"><a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Col%203.18" data-reference="Col 3.18" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Colossians 3:18</a> to <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Col%204.1" data-reference="Col 4.1" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Colossians 4:1</a>. </p>
    </b></font>
    <p align="justify">"<u>Wives</u>, submit to your husbands, as is fitting in 
    the Lord. <u><br>
    Husbands</u>, love your wives and do not be harsh with them. <br>
    <u>Children</u>, obey your parents in everything, for this pleases the Lord.
    <u><br>
    Fathers</u>, do not embitter your children, or they will become discouraged.
    <u><br>
    Servants</u>, obey your earthly masters in everything; and do it, not only 
    when their eye is on you and to win their favor, but with sincerity of heart 
    and reverence for the Lord. Whatever you do, work at it with all your heart, 
    as working for the Lord, not for men, since you know that you will receive 
    an inheritance from the Lord as a reward. It is the Lord Christ you are 
    serving.<u><br>
    Masters</u>, give unto your servants that which is just and equal; knowing 
    that you also have a Master in Heaven."</p>
    <p align="justify">IT is often a matter of complaint with some, that many 
    who have been ordained to preach the Gospel leave the great and mysterious 
    doctrines of the Gospel in the background, and bring forward little else 
    than dry <i>morality</i>. But, whatever ground there may be for that 
    complaint, it may be well to inquire, Whether there be not too much reason 
    to complain of another class, who pay such exclusive attention to the <i>
    doctrines</i>, as almost entirely to overlook the duties, of the Gospel? 
    Among some it would be almost thought superfluous, and even wrong, to devote 
    an entire discourse to the subject of moral duties; since, according to 
    their views, the discharge of them may well be left to the simple operation 
    of faith, without any distinct statement of them from the teachers of 
    Christianity. </p>
    <p align="justify">But the Apostle Paul did not think so. On the contrary, 
    in those two epistles (to the Ephesians, and Colossians) in which he enters 
    most deeply into the mysteries of Christianity, he enlarges most fully on 
    the relative duties. We are persuaded that a similar plan ought to be 
    adopted by every minister of Christ. We should have no exclusive preference 
    for doctrines or duties, but would put each in their place, and bring them 
    both forward in their proper season. Convinced of this, we enter with great 
    pleasure on the consideration of our <u>relative duties</u>; that is, of the 
    duties,</p>
    <font color="#0000ff"><b>
    <p align="justify">I. Of husbands and wives—</p>
    </b></font>
    <p align="justify">It is worthy of observation, that, not in this place 
    only, but in all other places where the Apostles speak of the relative 
    duties, they mention those of the inferior first. The reason of this seems 
    to be, that the duties of the inferior arise solely from the command of God, 
    and are totally independent of the conduct of the superior; so that no 
    neglect of duty on the one part can justify any neglect of it on the other. 
    Agreeably therefore to the Apostolic plan, we shall notice the duty,</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">1. Of wives—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">To you are assigned obedience and subjection. Partly, 
    because you were created after man, and for the sake of man; and partly 
    because you were first in the transgression, and were the means of bringing 
    ruin upon man and upon all his posterity, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Tim%202.11-14" data-reference="1 Tim 2.11-14" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Timothy 2:11-14</a> with <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Gen%203.16" data-reference="Gen 3.16" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Genesis 
    3:16</a>. The extent to which obedience to your husband is required of you is 
    indeed exceedingly great: it reaches to everything that is not contrary to 
    the will of God: it is, if I may so speak, co-extensive with the obedience 
    which the Church owes to the Lord Jesus Christ; and your obedience is due to 
    your husband, as to the Lord himself. </p>
    <p align="justify">I am aware that this expression is very strong; but I 
    conceive it is not at all stronger than the declarations of Paul. True, in 
    the text it is only said, "Submit yourselves, as it is fitting in the Lord:" 
    but in the Epistle to the Ephesians he draws the very parallel that I have 
    drawn, and shows that your duty to your husband corresponds exactly with the 
    Church's duty to the Lord Jesus Christ: "Wives, submit yourselves to your 
    own husbands, <u>as</u> unto the Lord: for the husband is the head of the 
    wife, even as Christ is the Head of the Church: and he is the Savior of the 
    body. Therefore, as the Church is subject unto Christ, so let the wives be 
    to their own husbands in everything, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Eph%205.22-24" data-reference="Eph 5.22-24" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ephesians 5:22-24</a>."</p>
    <p align="justify">In the whole of this obedience, she must feel that it is 
    due to him by God's special appointment: that he is her head, and her lord, 
    whom she is bound, not only to obey, but to obey with "respect, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Eph%205.33" data-reference="Eph 5.33" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ephesians 
    5:33</a>," "even as Sarah obeyed Abraham, calling him lord, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Pet%203.1" data-reference="1 Pet 3.1" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Peter 3:1</a>; <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Pet%203.5-6" data-reference="1 Pet 3.5-6" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Peter 
    3:5-6</a>."</p>
    <p align="justify">This may be thought to sound harsh by those who are not 
    accustomed to consider what the Scripture speaks on this subject: but it 
    will not be thought so, if we contemplate what God has required,</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">2. Of husbands—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">Your duty, is to "love your wives," and never on any 
    occasion to entertain an unkind feeling towards them. A proud, haughty, 
    imperious behavior towards them is most offensive to God, who will regard 
    every harsh, bitter, or contemptuous expression towards them as an abuse of 
    your authority and a violation of his commands. Though he has constituted 
    you <i>lords</i>, he has not authorized you to be <i>tyrants</i>; but 
    requires you to be precisely such lords over your wives, as Christ is over 
    his Church. You are to govern, it is true; but you are to govern only for 
    the good of the wife; you are to seek only, and at all times, her best 
    interests, and to promote to the utmost of your power her real happiness. 
    You must not require anything unreasonable at her hands, nor ever fail to 
    recompense with testimonies of your love, the efforts which she makes to 
    please you. Nor must you merely endeavor to render her happy, but you must 
    be ready to make great sacrifices for this end. </p>
    <p align="justify">What the Lord Jesus Christ has done for his Church, is 
    set forth as the proper model and pattern of your duty towards your wife: 
    "Husbands, love your wives, even as Christ also loved the Church, and gave 
    himself for it." O! what an example is here! Methinks, no wife would 
    complain of the obedience that is required of her, if the authority of her 
    husband were exercised in such a way as this! On the contrary, obedience on 
    her part would be her chief delight. </p>
    <p align="justify">Know then, you husbands, that this is the duty assigned 
    to you: if your wives are to be obedient, as the Church is to Christ—then 
    you also on your part are to be loving, even as Christ is to the Church. 
    Your wives should be to you as your own flesh. "Now no man ever yet hated 
    his own flesh, but nourishes and cherishes it, even as the Lord does the 
    Church, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Eph%205.28-29" data-reference="Eph 5.28-29" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ephesians 5:28-29</a>; <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Eph%205.33" data-reference="Eph 5.33" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ephesians 5:33</a>;" and precisely in the same way 
    should you exercise all imaginable tenderness towards your wives, and be as 
    careful of paining them as you would be of suffering anything to wound the 
    apple of your eye.</p>
    <p align="justify">Next to the duties of husbands and wives will naturally 
    follow those,</p>
    <font color="#0000ff"><b>
    <p align="justify">II. Of parents and children—</p>
    </b></font>
    <p align="justify">Here again we are called, in the first place, to notice 
    those of the inferior:</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">1. Of children—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">Obedience is your duty also: nor is there any limit to 
    the exercise of this duty, except where you are required to violate a 
    command of God. Reason indeed is sufficient to teach you this: for your own 
    ignorance and inexperience must of necessity direct you to look up to your 
    parents for instruction and guidance. But Scripture teaches you to regard 
    the authority of your parents as God's authority, and to consider obedience 
    to them as obedience to him. In fulfilling the commands of parents, there 
    should be no reluctance: on the contrary, to please, and serve, and honor 
    his parents would be the desire and delight of every child. He should have 
    no wish to shake off their yoke; no desire to act independently of them. </p>
    <p align="justify">Nor let this be thought hard: for God has annexed a 
    special promise to the fulfillment of this duty: the command relating to it 
    is said to be "the first commandment with promise, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Eph%206.1-3" data-reference="Eph 6.1-3" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ephesians 6:1-3</a>;" and it 
    is generally to be observed, that the blessing of God does rest in a more 
    especial manner, throughout the whole of their lives, on those who have 
    honored and obeyed their earthly parents. </p>
    <p align="justify">This may be accounted for on natural principles; for the 
    dispositions which are exercised in filial obedience argue a degree of 
    self-government, which will go far to render a man both amiable and 
    prosperous in every situation and condition of life. But besides this, the 
    blessing of God will assuredly rest on such characters; and He, as the 
    universal Parent, will recompense into their bosom their compliance with 
    this command.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">2. Of parents—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">Both in the text, and in the parallel passage in the 
    Epistle to the Ephesians, there is a restraint laid on parents with regard 
    to the exercise of their authority: it is not to be attended with harshness 
    or severity, "lest they provoke their children to anger, and discourage 
    them" from attempting to fulfill their duty, under the idea, that, whatever 
    efforts they may use to please their parents, it will he a hopeless task.
    </p>
    <p align="justify">Parents have much to answer for, when they produce such 
    an effect as this on their children's minds. If on the one hand it be said, 
    that "there is much folly in the heart of a child, and that the rod of 
    correction must drive it out;" it must be remembered, on the other hand, 
    that the mind of a child may soon be cast down, and that we may by harsh 
    restrictions and undue severity augment that very rebellion which we 
    endeavor to subdue. </p>
    <p align="justify">There can be no doubt but that many parents harden their 
    children's hearts against their authority in the first instance, and 
    ultimately against the authority of God himself, purely by the <i>tyranny
    </i>which they exercise, and by the continual irritations which they 
    occasion. That is a humiliating view which the Apostle gives of parents, 
    but, alas! how true in too many instances, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Heb%2012.10" data-reference="Heb 12.10" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hebrews 12:10</a>; and in the last 
    day they will be found, in too many instances, the prime movers, and the 
    real causes of their children's eternal ruin!</p>
    <p align="justify">Fathers, be upon your guard respecting this; and instead 
    of thus driving your children to despondency, endeavor to bring them up in 
    the "nurture and admonition of the Lord, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Eph%206.4" data-reference="Eph 6.4" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ephesians 6:4</a>." See in what way God 
    deals with His children, how he bears with their infirmities, and consults 
    their best interests, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Ps%20103.8-13" data-reference="Ps 103.8-13" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Psalm 103:8-13</a>; so would you do, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Thess%202.11" data-reference="1 Thess 2.11" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Thessalonians 2:11</a>; 
    and, like Abraham of old, be solicitous only for their eternal welfare, 
    <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Gen%2018.19" data-reference="Gen 18.19" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Genesis 18:19</a>.</p>
    <p align="justify">There is yet one other relation specified in the text, 
    namely, that,</p>
    <font color="#0000ff"><b>
    <p align="justify">III. Of masters and servants—</p>
    </b></font>
    <p align="justify">It has pleased God that there should be different ranks 
    and orders of society, and that to each would be assigned appropriate 
    duties. We notice those,</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">1. Of servants—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">Your rank in society is ordered by the Lord: nor, when 
    you hear in what light you are viewed by him, will you see any reason to 
    repine at it. By virtue of your office you are required to "obey those who 
    are your masters according to the flesh:" and to obey them cheerfully too, 
    and without reserve. Nor in the discharge of this duty are you to act in the 
    absence of your master any other way than you would in his immediate 
    presence; you are to render obedience "in singleness of heart, as unto 
    Christ; not with eye-service, as men-pleasers, but as the servants of 
    Christ, doing the will of God from the heart, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Eph%206.5-6" data-reference="Eph 6.5-6" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ephesians 6:5-6</a>." </p>
    <p align="justify">What an elevated view does this give of your situation 
    and employments! You appear to be servants of men: and so indeed you are. 
    But you are servants of the Lord Jesus Christ: and it is your privilege to 
    consider yourselves as living in his service, as much as if he were to come 
    down to sojourn again on earth, and to admit you into the number of his 
    servants. Whatever your particular office is, you are privileged, so to 
    speak, as altogether to forget your servitude to man, and to consider 
    yourselves as performing the office of angels in the service of your God and 
    Savior. </p>
    <p align="justify">It is your privilege also to expect your wages from Him. 
    What you receive from man, is for your body only: but you shall have wages 
    for your soul also, even "the reward of an eternal inheritance!" This is 
    represented as the state even of slaves, and of those who were called to 
    serve Jewish or Heathen masters. How much more then is it the happy state of 
    you who live in Christian families, and especially where God in Christ Jesus 
    is loved and feared! Yes, "whether you be bond or free, your Master, your 
    work, your wages are the same, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Eph%206.8" data-reference="Eph 6.8" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ephesians 6:8</a>." Act then agreeably to this 
    exalted view of your station. Even though you would have "froward and unkind 
    masters," still act the same: and, if your <i>work </i>is thereby rendered 
    the more difficult, your <i>reward </i>shall be proportionably advanced, 1 
    Peter 2:18-20.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">2. Of masters—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">As your servants are to put you in the place of Christ, 
    so are you to be as in the place of Christ to them. Exactly such a muster as 
    he, if in your place, would be, such are you to be to those who are under 
    your command. </p>
    <p align="justify">Would he never be unreasonable in his expectations or 
    commands? So neither are you to be. </p>
    <p align="justify">Would he be kind and indulgent? So must you be. </p>
    <p align="justify">Would he delight to make his servants happy; and would he 
    consult in all things their eternal welfare? So are you to act, "doing in 
    your station the same thing in them," as they in theirs are required to do 
    to you, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Eph%206.9" data-reference="Eph 6.9" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ephesians 6:9</a>. </p>
    <p align="justify">Especially must you "forbear all threatening" words or 
    looks, "remembering that you also have a Master in Heaven, with whom there 
    is no respect of persons," and who, as their avenger, will call you to an 
    account for all acts of unkindness or oppression towards the basest of 
    mankind. In a word, see how your God directs and governs you; and let him be 
    your model for your government of those whom he has graciously committed to 
    your care.</p>
    <b><font color="#0000ff">
    <p align="justify">We may see here,</p>
    </font>
    <p align="justify">1. The extent and excellence of true religion—</p>
    </b><i>
    </i><p align="justify"><i>Religion enters into every situation and relation of life</i>. 
    It finds the whole world disordered like a body, every joint of which from 
    head to foot is dislocated: but by its operation on the hearts of men, it 
    sets every joint in its place, and diffuses through the whole a divine 
    unction, whereby every joint is set at liberty, and performs with ease its 
    proper functions. </p>
    <p align="justify">Those in a higher and more honorable station despise not 
    those which are lower and less honorable; neither are they envied by them: 
    but each occupies with contentment and satisfaction the place assigned it by 
    its Maker, and finds its own happiness in contributing, according to its 
    ability, to the good of the whole. </p>
    <p align="justify">If it is said that these effects are not visible in the 
    world, even among those who profess religion; I answer, that this only shows 
    how little there is of true religion in the world!</p>
    <p align="justify">The first ages of the Church display in all its beauty 
    the native tendency of Christianity: and, if the same effects are not alike 
    visible now, it is not owing to any lack of efficiency in religion itself, 
    but to the low state of religion in the world. <i>In proportion as vital 
    godliness prevails, it does, and ever must, manifest its practical influence 
    upon the heart and life.</i></p><i>
    </i><b>
    <p align="justify">2. The importance of studying the character of Christ—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">Christ ought to be well known to us in his work and 
    offices as the only Savior of the world. But we must not confine our 
    attention to his mediatorial work: we must also contemplate him as an <i>
    example </i>which we are to follow in every part of our conduct both towards 
    God and man. </p>
    <p align="justify">Behold him as a son and a servant; what an entire 
    devotion was there in him to his Father's will! It was his food and drink to 
    do it. </p>
    <p align="justify">View him also as the Husband and Lord of his Church; what 
    inconceivable love and kindness does he exercise towards her at all times, 
    notwithstanding her innumerable defects! Let us then study his character; 
    and whether we move in the higher or inferior relation, let it be the one 
    aim of our lives to walk in his steps, and to follow his example.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">3. The way in which to judge of our spiritual 
    attainments—</p>
    </b><i>
    </i><p align="justify"><i>Religion is a practical thing, and is intended, as we 
    have shown, to make us fill to advantage every relation in life.</i> Now I 
    grant that there are many who discharge in a most commendable manner their 
    relative duties, while yet they have no regard for God in their hearts. 
    Consequently, I cannot exactly say that the fulfillment of relative duties 
    will stamp you as pious characters: but this I must say, that the <i>not </i>
    discharging of these aright will prove to demonstration, either that "your 
    religion is altogether vain," or that it is at a very low ebb indeed. </p>
    <p align="justify">But supposing that there be no manifest neglect of these 
    duties, I would ask: How much is there of God in them? Is the authority 
    which you either obey or exercise, regarded as God's? Is <i>his will </i>
    considered as the rule of all that you do, and <i>his glory </i>as the end? 
    Here is the point to be inquired into: it is this which makes your actions 
    pleasing and acceptable to him: and I may add, that it is this which will 
    make obedience easy and delightful to yourselves. </p>
    <p align="justify">Habituate yourselves then to realize the thought that it 
    is Christ whom you serve, or in whose place you stand while others are 
    serving you. So shall your whole deportment become exquisitely pure, and 
    holy, and refined; and you will "adorn the doctrine of God our Savior in all 
    things!"</p>
    <p align="justify">&nbsp;</p>
    <font color="#ff0000"><b>
    <p align="justify">#2190</p>
    <p align="justify">THE CHARACTER AND AIM OF A CHRISTIAN MINISTER</p>
    <p align="justify"><a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Col%204.12" data-reference="Col 4.12" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Colossians 4:12</a> </p>
    </b></font>
    <p align="justify">"Epaphras, who is one of you, a servant of Christ, greets 
    you, always laboring fervently for you in prayers, that you may stand 
    perfect and complete in all the will of God."</p>
    <p align="justify">LOVE is the essence of the Christian religion. The 
    heathen themselves noticed the fervor of the love which existed among the 
    first Christians. Ministers in particular feel a distinguished regard for 
    those to whom they have been signally useful, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Thess%202.7-8" data-reference="1 Thess 2.7-8" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Thessalonians 2:7-8</a>. 
    Epaphras is set forth as a most eminent pattern of affection and zeal.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">I. The office he sustained—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">Epaphras was perhaps the same with Epaphroditus. He was 
    of Colosse, and perhaps the founder of the Church established there; he 
    sustained the most honorable of all offices, being "a <i>servant </i>of 
    Christ." This office every Christian may be said to bear, but ministers bear 
    it in a higher and more exalted sense. They are,</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">1. His stewards—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">A steward has the care and management of the family 
    committed to him: so Christ's ministers have the mysteries of the Gospel 
    committed to them, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/2%20Cor%204.7" data-reference="2 Cor 4.7" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2 Corinthians 4:7</a>. They are to dispense these mysteries 
    to men, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Luke%2012.42" data-reference="Luke 12.42" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Luke 12:42</a>; hence we are taught to consider them expressly in this 
    view, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Cor%204.1" data-reference="1 Cor 4.1" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Corinthians 4:1</a>.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">2. His messengers—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">They are ambassadors from the court of Heaven, 2 
    Corinthians 5:19-20; they deliver to men his messages of grace and mercy: 
    they negotiate, as it were, a peace between God and man.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">3. His representatives—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">They stand in his stead, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/2%20Cor%205.20" data-reference="2 Cor 5.20" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2 Corinthians 5:20</a>; the word 
    they speak is not theirs, but his, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Thess%202.13" data-reference="1 Thess 2.13" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Thessalonians 2:13</a>. The reception or 
    rejection of them will be deemed a reception or rejection of Christ himself, 
    <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Thess%204.8" data-reference="1 Thess 4.8" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Thessalonians 4:8</a>.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">4. His glory—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">They are the instruments whereby he is known and 
    glorified: hence they are expressly called "the glory of Christ, 2 
    Corinthians 8:23."</p>
    <p align="justify">In this office he acted worthy of the trust reposed in 
    him.</p>
    <font color="#0000ff"><b>
    <p align="justify">II. The love he manifested—</p>
    </b></font><i>
    </i><p align="justify"><i>Love will invariably manifest itself in acts of kindness 
    towards those who are the objects of it. </i>A minister's love will show 
    itself most towards the souls of men; but none can do good to souls unless 
    God himself grants his blessing, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Cor%203.7" data-reference="1 Cor 3.7" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Corinthians 3:7</a>; hence Epaphras made 
    application to God in prayer.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">He did this fervently—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">It is said of Jacob that he "wrestled" with God all night 
    in prayer. Compare <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Gen%2032.24" data-reference="Gen 32.24" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Genesis 32:24</a>; <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Gen%2032.28" data-reference="Gen 32.28" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Genesis 32:28</a> with <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Hos%2012.4" data-reference="Hos 12.4" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hosea 12:4</a>. Thus did 
    Epaphras on behalf of the Christians at Colosse. How desirable is it that 
    every minister would be so occupied!</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">He did it constantly—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">He was not satisfied with preaching to them, or praying 
    with them: he remembered them "always" in his secret prayers before God, 1 
    Thessalonians 3:10 with <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Isa%2062.7" data-reference="Isa 62.7" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Isaiah 62:7</a>; nor did his absence from them diminish 
    his concern for their welfare. This was the most unequivocal testimony of 
    his affection that he could possibly give them. <i>It is easier to preach to 
    men ten hours, than to pray for them one!</i></p><i>
    </i>
    <p align="justify">Nor could he rest satisfied, while his people had sins to 
    forsake, or spiritual needs to be supplied.</p>
    <font color="#0000ff"><b>
    <p align="justify">III. The end he aimed at—</p>
    </b></font>
    <p align="justify">He desired that his Christian friends might be <i>
    Israelites indeed</i>; no doubt he had exerted himself much and often to 
    make them so. He sought the same blessed end in all his prayers for them:</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">1. That they might have no secret reserves in their 
    obedience—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">He well knew that <i>one sin indulged would destroy the 
    soul</i>, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Jer%2048.10" data-reference="Jer 48.10" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Jeremiah 48:10</a>. He was aware that nothing but the most unreserved 
    dedication of ourselves to God's service would be of any avail <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Ps%20119.6" data-reference="Ps 119.6" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Psalm 119:6</a>. 
    He therefore prayed that they might do "all" the will of God.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">2. That they might attain the highest degrees of 
    holiness—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">There is no absolute perfection or completeness in the 
    creature; but there are high degrees of holiness to which the upright may 
    attain. He wished them not to continue babes, but to arrive at a state of 
    manhood; and not to be satisfied with a scanty measure of grace and 
    knowledge, but to be "filled with all the fullness of God." He longed that 
    they might be as eminent in piety as possible, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/1%20Thess%205.23" data-reference="1 Thess 5.23" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 Thessalonians 5:23</a>.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">3. That they might be steadfast to the end—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">Many "endure only for a season, and in a time of 
    temptation fall away;" but the apostatizing of persons who have been 
    hopeful, is death, as it were, to a faithful minister of Christ, 1 
    Thessalonians 3:8. He knew that there were many seeking to turn them from 
    the faith, <a class="rtBibleRef" href="https://biblia.com/bible/niv/Col%202.8" data-reference="Col 2.8" data-version="niv" data-purpose="bible-reference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Colossians 2:8</a>; he therefore sought to have them so established 
    that they might "stand."</p>
    <b><font color="#0000ff">
    <p align="justify">We may observe from hence,</p>
    </font>
    <p align="justify">1. What should be the standard of a minister's preaching—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">Faithful ministers are often thought too strict and 
    severe; but if they would desire such spiritual maturity for their people, 
    they would labor also to promote it by their preaching. If they would lower 
    the standard of men's duty, they would betray and murder the souls committed 
    to them! Let not any then condemn the strictness or severity of what they 
    hear, unless it exceeds the Scripture standard.</p>
    <b>
    <p align="justify">2. What should be the measure of the people's practice—</p>
    </b>
    <p align="justify">There is no attainment with which we would be satisfied, 
    while there remains anything to be attained. What ministers would desire for 
    us, we ought to desire and aim at for ourselves. Whatever then we may have 
    attained, let us forget what is behind, and press forward toward that which 
    is ahead!</p>